<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A token for mariners containing many famous and wonderful instances of God's providence in sea dangers and deliverances, in mercifully preserving the lives of his poor creatures, when, in humane probability, at the point of perishing by shipwrack, famine, or other accidents. much enlarg'd, with the addition of many new relations, one whereof happening this present year, and never before printed. Mostly attested by the persons themselves. Also The seaman's preacher, being a sermon on the right improvement of such mercies. And prayers for seamen on all occasions.</title>
            <author>Janeway, James, 1636?-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58039</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222746</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833884</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833884</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38362</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58039)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38362)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2215:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A token for mariners containing many famous and wonderful instances of God's providence in sea dangers and deliverances, in mercifully preserving the lives of his poor creatures, when, in humane probability, at the point of perishing by shipwrack, famine, or other accidents. much enlarg'd, with the addition of many new relations, one whereof happening this present year, and never before printed. Mostly attested by the persons themselves. Also The seaman's preacher, being a sermon on the right improvement of such mercies. And prayers for seamen on all occasions.</title>
                  <author>Janeway, James, 1636?-1674.</author>
                  <author>Ryther, John, 1634?-1681, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 155, [5] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Hugh Newman, and sold at his shop at the Grashopper in the Poultry,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By James Janeway; attributed by Wing to John Ryther.</note>
                  <note>Copy tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Congregational Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sailors --  Religious life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:38362:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38362:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:38362:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>A Token for Mariners</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:38362:2"/>
A TOKEN FOR <hi>MARINERS,</hi> CONTAINING Many Famous and Wonderful In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of <hi>God's Providence</hi> in <hi>Sea Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> and <hi>Deliverances,</hi> in Mercifully preſerving the Lives of his poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, when, in Humane Probability, at the Point of Periſhing by <hi>Shipwrack, Famine,</hi> or other <hi>Accidents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much Enlarg'd, with the <hi>Addition</hi> of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny New <hi>Relations,</hi> one whereof happening this Preſent Year, and never before Printed. <hi>Moſtly Attested by the Perſons Themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO The <hi>Seaman's Preacher,</hi> Being a <hi>Sermon</hi> on the Right Improvement of ſuch MERCIES. And <hi>Prayers for Seamen on all Occaſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Hugh Newman,</hi> and Sold at his Shop at the <hi>Graſhopper</hi> in the <hi>Poultry.</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:38362:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38362:3"/>
            <head>THE Preface <hi>to the</hi> Reader. And Particularly to <hi>Mariners,</hi> and other <hi>Seafaring-Men.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>THough God's Wonders are every where viſible, and his Mercies no where hid from the Eyes of Men; yet more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are they Evident to Sea-faring Men, whoſe Buſineſs is in the Great Waters, and their Lives Expoſed more than others to Iunume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable hazards and dangers, of</hi> Contending Winds <hi>and</hi> Seas, Rocks, Quickſands, <hi>and</hi> Inhoſpitable Shoaers: <hi>Theſe, as it were, carry their Lives in their hands, and their beſt Security is Wholly to Rely on the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Protection of him</hi> whoſe Power the Winds and Waves obey: <hi>Seeing there is ſo ſmall a partition between them and Eternity, the Striking on a Treacherous</hi> Rock, <hi>over which, many times, the Flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Water ſmoothly glides, gives them their
<pb facs="tcp:38362:4"/>
Winding-ſheet in a Rumpled Wave. Nor is this all their danger, the Springing of a Plank, a Leak not to be found, nor ſuddenly ſtopped, Running on a Shoal, or the Falling of a Water-ſpout, frequently carry with them the ſame Inevitable Fate, and often makes them at their Wits Ends before they end their Lives; for, a certain Proſpect of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable Death muſt needs be Terrible to Fleſh and Blood, and, in a great meaſure, remove that Conſtant Preſence of Mind that ſhould ſupport their Spirits amidſt all Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: From this there is no way to ſecure themſelves, but by laying hold on him that is Mighty, and able to ſave to the utmoſt, on God, who is a preſent help at need, whoſe eyes are in all places, in Heaven and Earth, and in the Great Deep; and thoſe that Cry to him in their Diſtreſs, he will ſurely hear them and Deliver them out of all their Troubles, if they are ſincere in heart, and walk uprightly with him. For a Praying-</hi>Paul's <hi>ſake, we find, though the Ship was broken, and periſhed on a Rock on the Coaſt of the Iſland, antient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> Melita, <hi>now called</hi> Malta, <hi>all that were in it were ſaved, when they expected nothing leſs than to be ſwallowed up in that dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Ocean, as we find it in the</hi> Acts, <hi>Chap. 27. Therefore the beſt thing I can Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to</hi> Mariners, <hi>and others that Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate
<pb facs="tcp:38362:4"/>
the Deep, is to have a ſtedfaſt Relyance on God in all their Dangers, nay, at all times, for that is the beſt and ſureſt Anchor-hold and Security that can be had recourſe to, and therefore I have furniſhed this Book with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Wonderful and Remarkable</hi> Sea-Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, <hi>to ſhow them that their hopes are not in vain; for, the Wonders he has already wrought, he will doubtleſs continue to all that fear and put their Truſt in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> Collection <hi>is taken moſtly from the Mouths of thoſe who have experienc'd God's Mercy this way, and whoſe Dangers have been as great as any could be on this ſide the Grave; yet God, in his Mercy, delivered them out of all. The reſt are taken from ſuch Reverend</hi> Authors, <hi>that their Credit and Integrity is Indiſputable, being purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Written to raiſe the Minds of Men to Contemplate and Adore the Love and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the All-wiſe Creator of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe, and may indifferently ſerve to this end as well at</hi> Land <hi>as</hi> Sea, <hi>though chiefly intended for</hi> Sea-faring <hi>Men, to put them in Mind, when they Read it, of their Danger, and what they may expect in their Danger, from the Death they apprehend in it, if they apply their hearts to true Wiſdom. When all help or hopes fail, or ſeem to be at a loſs, then fix your hearts and eyes ſtedfaſtly on him who is
<pb facs="tcp:38362:5"/>
able to do all things, and to whom nothing is impoſſible; on him, in whoſe hands is all the Breath of Life, who can ſtop the ſhafts of Death in their winged motion, check the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Thunder in the Midd-Volley, and turn the Raging of the Winds to a ſudden Calm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But not to be Tedious in a</hi> Preface; <hi>I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend this to you, as a ſuitable Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in your Voyages or Travels, nay in your houſes, or at all times, that you may know theſe things are the Lord's doing, tho they are Marvellous in our eyes. And ſo Conclude, ſubſcribing my ſelf,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
               <signed>Your Friend and Servant, J. J.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38362:5"/>
            <head>REMARKABLE SEA <hi>Deliverances.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ONe Major <hi>Gibbons,</hi> a man well known in <hi>new England,</hi> a Gentleman of good educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, good parts, and of good Converſation, (as the Author hath been credibly informed by them that knew him) was bound upon a voyage to Sea, himſelf being <hi>Supra Cargo</hi> with ſuch commoditys as thoſe parts of <hi>America</hi> doth afford, after going out from <hi>Boſton</hi> ſeveral days, by hard weather, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary winds, the Ships company were much diſtreſſed, and through the Continuance of the contrary winds Proviſions now begin to faile them; and O how feeble doth Spirit
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38362:6"/>
grow, when Bread, the Staffe of life faileth! now Hunger becomes more dreadfull to them, then the every moment threatning Billows of the devouring Ocean; and they that one while feared drowning, now fears Starving; they are brought to the laſt meal in the Barrel, and the laſt oyl in the Cruſe, and ſay as ſhe did <hi>We will Eat this little that is left, and dye:</hi> and now when they thought they had eaten the laſt, what conflicts muſt they needs have within themſelves? who knew not where to have another morſel to fortify the tyred and ſpent Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits with the conſtant toyl, and hard la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: how they look one upon another, as men already under a Sentence of death; and by one anothers looks, Strike terror to one anothers Hearts; They look on every ſide, Pſal. 142. 4, 5. (as <hi>David</hi> ſays) <hi>I looked on my right hand, but there was no man that would know me; Refuge failed me;</hi> or periſhed from me. They look downward, and ſee nothing but the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of deſtruction opening for them; they look upward, the onely, and laſt refuge, and remedy, in this deplorable eſtate was, out of the depths, they cry'd to the Lord,</p>
            <p>But though they look out of the Ship, as <hi>Noah</hi> did out of his Ark, upon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38362:6"/>
and ſend forth the Dove of Prayer, that winged Meſſenger, to Heaven, yet ſhe brings no Olive branch, no Anſwer; the waters aſſwage not, the winds calm not, they are like the Prophets Servant, when he bid him 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. 43. <hi>go up now; and look to-wards the Sea, and he went up and looked and ſaid, there is nothing;</hi> and this ſtrikes them into dolefull and diſmall La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations; out of which Lamentations, at laſt Springs up a tragical and ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Motion. The Motion is, that which the Marriners, in <hi>Jonahs</hi> Veſſel, put in execution, <hi>Come let us caſt Lots, &amp;c.</hi> only with this difference, they caſt Lots to find out the dilinquent; and theſe, which of them ſhould dye firſt, to be a Sacrifice for ravenous Hunger to feed upon: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding, as he in that caſe, <hi>John.</hi> 11. 50. <hi>It is expedient for us that one man ſhould dye for the People, and that the whole Ships Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany periſh not.</hi> Life being ſweet, Skin for Skin, and all a man hath will he give for his life, they at laſt bring it, through many a ſad debate, to a reſult, they caſt the Lott, the diſpoſing of which is of the Lord; one of the Company is arreſted by the Lott; here is the Condemned Priſoner: O but where is the Executioner to be found to act his office upon a poor Innocent? is it not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38362:7"/>
death to them now, to think who ſhall act this bloody part in the Tragedy? But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they fall upon their involuntary Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, Major <hi>Gibbons</hi> calls them to Prayer, conſidering, that in the Mount, the Lord is often ſeen, and that many times our extremity proves Gods opportunity; he alſo askes the poor man if he was willing to dye; but O what a hard Queſtion is that to Anſwer! He replys, if it might preſerve the reſt of the lives, he could be the more willing; to which he hath this Anſwer: All events are in the hands of God, we muſt not diſpute them, to Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer they go: and, O ſure theſe Prayers muſt melt hearts of Adamant! and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, while they are at it, God ſends a viſible commentary upon that Scripture: <hi>Eſay</hi> 58. 9. <hi>Then ſhalt thou call, and the Lord ſhall Anſwer; thou ſhalt Cry, and he ſhall ſay here I am:</hi> For while they were calling, God was Anſwering; there leaps a mighty Fiſh into the Boat; and as it is ſaid of the Whale: that ſwallowed up <hi>Jonah, God prepared a Fiſh,</hi> for the Lord here prepared, or provided a Fiſh, that a poor creature might not be ſwallowed up: but O what joy was here at ſuch a token for good! not only it at preſent releiving and refreſhing their huuger, which no Queſton
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38362:7"/>
made them quick Cooks; but when they looked upon the Finger of God in it, ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it as an anſwer to prayer, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it an happy Omen of their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and a pledg of approaching mercy: but alas, it is not long before their hearts grow faint again, their Countenances pale, their Spirits ſink now as low as they were lifted up high; and now the poor Sea-men are like their Ship, one while mounted up in the hopes to Heaven, and another while they are ſunk down again in deſpair as low as hell; they know not now of another cake, another Morſell, they are reduced to their former exigency, which brings them to a reſolve to ſteer in this ſtrait their old courſe; to Lotts they go again the Second time, only they have ſuch an honour for the Providence of God, they will not put him into condemnation, that God hath acquited; the Lott now falls upon another perſon, and O now they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the old trouble, and inteſtine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats, how they ſhall find in their Hearts, to puniſh one, that never had offended any of them; and while one thinks of it, ſayes he, Alas poor man, what hath he done to deſerve this ſentence? another crys, Will not this blood cleave to my Conſcience another day? though I went to this expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38362:8"/>
a Preſt Souldier? another ſays, for his part he ſees no way but death, therefore he cannot take away life, when he ſees not any life can be preſerved by it: but they are called again to look upward, before they put the Knife to the Throat of this Sacrifice, and they remember the laſt encouragement to put life into the almoſt dead-mens Prayers; they pray now with a pledge in their hands, and are ready to tell God, the laſt time he gave them a Pawn, an Earneſt; and O it is not vain to ſeek the Lord! for lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, while they are ſeeking to him, he is ſending to them; as the Prayers flye to Heaven, Mercy is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched upon the wing from Heaven.</p>
            <p>O turn aſide, and ſee this great ſight, while they are praying. Behold a ſecond Anſwer from above; A great Bird lights and fixes her ſelf upon the Maſt, which one in the Company eſpies, and up he goes and there ſhe ſtands until he took her with his hand by the wing, &amp; brought her down to the Company; and O what life from the dead is this to them a ſecond time! Sure they will hearken to the voyce of the ſecond Sign, if not to the voyce of the firſt; and now that which they hoped by the firſt Providence <hi>(viz)</hi> that it was a fore-runner of the compleat delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; Now they are by this ſecond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38362:8"/>
in the Faith, and now they begin to think (as I can eaſily imagin) if God will ſave them out of this diſtreſs, O what manner of perſons they will become! what manner of lives they will live! what Sacrifices of Thankſgiving will they offer up to God! but while they are thus think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they have no viſible hopes, but that it muſt be a third Miracle that brings them out of this their miſerable condition; they have the ſame diſappointments upon them ſtill, only now they divert their Hunger all they can, by telling of, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the Loaves, (as I may ſay) their experiences in this extremity of theirs, and comforting themſelves, that if they come to a third ſtrait, it would (they hoped) be an outlet from their preſent miſery and calamity: They are reduced the third time to the former courſe and ſtrait, to caſt Lotts; and when they were to go to the heart-aking work, to put him to death, upon whom the Lott fell, they go to their Old Friend, in a day of Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, (to God) by hearty and humble Prayer; And O now they do, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets man at the Sea-ſide, look again and again, but alas Maſter they cry, <hi>there is nothing.</hi> Prayer is done, concluded, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing appears; O but as the Prophets
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38362:9"/>
Man looked ſeaven times, ſo ſays this good man Major <hi>Gibbons,</hi> look again, as <hi>Jonah,</hi> I will look again towards his Holy Temple (ſays he to one of the Company) <hi>Go up to the top, and ſee what you can eſpy;</hi> and at laſt he makes a Sayl, <hi>(viz.)</hi> eſpys a Ship; this puts new life into all their ſpirits; they bear up with the Veſſel, they Man their Boat, they deſire, in the manner of periſhing humble Suppliants, to Board them, which they are Admitted; the Veſſel proves a <hi>French</hi> Veſſel, yea, a <hi>French</hi> Pyrate; Major <hi>Gibbons</hi> Petitions him for a little Bread to ſuſtain their lives, who had been ſeveral days wiſhing for death, but could not find it in their Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; and take the Ship and Cargo. So ſweet is life, that all that a man hath will he give for his life; and now behold, God draws forth to theſe Poor Periſhing men his beſt Wine to the laſt, nay, turns the Water of Affliction into the Wine of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. The Commander of the Veſſel knows the Major, and replys readily and chearfully, Major <hi>Gibbons,</hi> not one hair of your head ſhall periſh, nor any of your Ships Company, if it lye in my power ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſupply you, or preſerve you. O the Wiſdom of God that hath ways we know not of, to Relieve in the greateſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38362:9"/>
ſtraits, and cauſe himſelf to be ſeen in the Mount. The Commander of this <hi>French</hi> Pyrat was one that ſome years before, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor <hi>Gibbons</hi> had ſhown ſignal Kindneſs to, when his life was in danger at <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New England.</hi> Thus the Lord appeared a God, hearing Prayers in Extremitys, which appearances are not to be forgotten in ſucceeding Generations. O that men would praiſe the Lord for his goodneſs, and for his wonderful works to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men.</p>
            <p>Secondly. About the year 1636. there ariſing a ſtorm and tempeſt of troubles in the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> five Miniſters, eminent for Piety, Learning, and their Honourable ſucceſs in the Miniſtry, were ſo hard born under by a prevailing Party impoſing upon their Conſciences, that they were forced to Embarque them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for <hi>America;</hi> three of their names were Mr. <hi>Levinſton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Mackleland;</hi> and Mr. <hi>Blaire,</hi> with two more whom my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor could not call to mind.</p>
            <p>Theſe good men Say<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d half the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel over, about 500. Leagues, where they met with great diſtreſs of weather, which broke off the Rudder of their Ship, and occaſioned a deſperate leak to ſpring in her, which expoſed them to eminent
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38362:10"/>
danger; but they in this diſtreſs endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to hang on their Rudder again, but often were they fruſtrated in their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, to a total deſpair of effecting it. They alſo laboured with the like unſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfulneſs to find out and ſtop the leak; this poor Ships Crew had laboured alſo by pumping, to keep the Ship above wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, until all their few hands were feeble, and all their hearts faint; ſo that as ſo many <hi>diſpairing perſons</hi> of life, they ceaſe all endeavours, and yield themſelves to death, expecting every moment to be En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tombed in the belly of the devouring deeps; during the time of this their great diſtreſs, the Miniſters kept on their courſe, as at other times of Worſhip, <hi>(viz)</hi> the reading of a Chapter in courſe, and taking obſervations from it, with Prayers and Preaching, which they did by turns; at the criſis of this deplorable caſe, it fell to be the Lott of Mr. <hi>Mackleland</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form this Exerciſe, a man Auſteer in his life, reſerved in his ſpeech, and of great Piety, who was often obſerved to let fall many remarkable Prophetical Expreſſions of future events; the Chapter that at that time came to be read in courſe by him, was the 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Exodus,</hi> which he had read all along (until he came to the 12th.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38362:10"/>
               <hi>verſe.)</hi> where he made a full ſtop; the verſes run thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> Moſes <hi>beſought the Lord his God, and ſaid, Lord, why doth thy Wrath wax hot againſt thy people, which thou haſt brought out of the Land of</hi> Egypt <hi>with great Power, and a mighty hand? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould the Egyptians ſay, for miſchief did he bring them out to ſlay them in the Mountains, and to conſume them from the face of the Earth? Turn from thy ſevere Wrath, and repent of this Evil againſt thy People,—</hi>upon the reading of theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes over again he declared to them, the Caſe which <hi>Moſes</hi> was here intercee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for, compared with his Expoſtula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the 12 verſe, did parallel their caſe, and conſidering the happy event of that Argument, which <hi>Moſes</hi> uſed (mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the 14 verſe, which runs thus:) <hi>and the Lord Repented of the Evil which he thought to doe unto his People—</hi>he could not but comfortably hope, that they might have the ſame Effect: Nay he goes further, and his Spirit raiſed into a peremptory prediction, that he durſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them from his great Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that not one hair of their heads ſhould fall to the ground; after this he went to Prayer, urging God with the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38362:11"/>
ſame Argument, and then roſe up com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably aſſuring his ſtedfaſtneſs in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving the ſame; he adviſes the Sea-men and the Company in the Ship to refreſh themſelves by taking ſome meat, the long faſting and hard labour having much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feebled them. Then he encouraged them to make another Attempt to faſten the Rudder, without which they could not poſſible make towards any point for ſhore. He after adviſed them to clear the ſhip, as well as they could, from wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by pumping, which they did happily Effect, the Leak being ſtopt providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially of it ſelf—whether it was ſome noak of a plank ſtarted by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs of weather which occaſioned the Leak, and by the ſurges of the Sea, clapt into the place again, or what it was elſe could not be known. But however this lookes like life from the dead to theſe poor men, who had received but a little before a ſentence of Death in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they might truſt in him who raiſeth the Dead. Soon after this, God who had heard in Heaven great Tears and Prayers, Commands the Wind Tack about to the Weſt, and to blow ſo ſtrong a gale that they were forced to bear up before it, and it continued ſo
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38362:11"/>
long, that it brought them back to the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> where they continued ſome time; although but ſhort, they were very inſtrumental in the Converting of many ſouls, which ſeed-plot remains to this day; and ſoon after they paſſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Scotland.</hi> This Relation was given by ſeveral Miniſters of the North of <hi>Ireland:</hi> alſo the Reader may take notice, the Author of that Book called the <hi>Full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the Scriptures,</hi> pag. 487. mentions this remarkable Providence, though not ſo largely, with theſe two additional, but very conſiderable circumſtances; firſt, That a poor Sea-man was made the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to preſerve the ſame Veſſel, by faſtening the Rudder, whoſe company they had all ſhun'd, others having given it over. Secondly, Several Paſſengers being Aboard, who ſhipt themſelves for <hi>America,</hi> upon only external accounts, expecting a fat ſoyle, and outward ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage in that place, and not as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers upon the account of Conſcience, to enjoy the purity of Ordinances; they did all dye upon the Sea ſave one, being five in number. And who is ſo blind, as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee here the out ſtretched Arm of an Omnipotent God, commanding delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance for his poor diſtreſſed, perſecuted,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38362:12"/>
praying, believing Servants, and alſo for all them that Sayled with them? O who would not Pray at Sea, and truſt in him who raiſes the dead in the ſaddeſt of their Extremities and diſtreſs! and ſpeaks forth much of the power and goodneſs of God, calling upon all to truſt in him, let the dangers and ſtraits be never ſo great.</p>
            <p>3. A Veſſel of ours about the year 1636. being at New-found Land a Fiſhing, being ſomewhat of the lateſt in the year, until the Ice came in great flakes; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready to hoiſe Sayle for the return home, they ſent out in the Boat ſix of the men to weigh their Anchor; but while they were about it, a ſad Providence pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents them, a great flake of Ice interpoſes between them and their ſhip, and carryes them adrift, ſo that by all means that they and the ſhip could uſe, they could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their Veſſel again, whereby they were expoſed to an inevitable ruine, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther having Food, nor any other Accomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to keep them warm; they having continued thus three daysand three nights, they began to be Hunger-ſtarv'd, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting themſelves all dead men, they began to conſult one with another what courſe to take; they at laſt, though with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38362:12"/>
great regret and grief, reſolve one of them muſt dye to become Food for the reſt; each perſon begg'd to have it his Lot to dye firſt, to be freed from that tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that they languiſhed under; ſo that they were forced to determine it by Lot: He upon whom the Lot fell, deſired to go to one end of the Boat, there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend his ſoul to God by Prayer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he dyed; the reſt being in a deep A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gony upon apprehenſion of ſhedding the blood of one of their Comerades: But while they were ſat together, lamenting and imploring God's favour to prevent ſuch a fact according to that they wiſhed and deſired: The perſon ſeparated by Lot for death, dyed upon the place where he was praying, which in their deplorable Condition occaſioned great Joy to the reſt, that hereby they were not forced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their wills to take his life; ſo look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon this as a good <hi>Omen,</hi> they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to ſatisfie their Hungers upon the dead body: the Boat was ſtill A-drift, not frozen up; ſo that by that time, their Food was ſpent, they were brought aſhore many Leagues to the Norward of <hi>New-England,</hi> where the five landed alive, where the poor <hi>Barbarians</hi> did commiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them, and help them as they could;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38362:13"/>
three of them dyed with the diſtreſs they had been in, the other two made a ſhift to get to <hi>New-England,</hi> and ſo at laſt, by a good hand of God upon them, came to their Habitations in the Weſt of <hi>England,</hi> having both loſt their heels with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of the cold in the Boat. This Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation my Author had from one of theſe two Sea-men, with whom he came after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a Paſſenger from <hi>Ireland,</hi> to whom he ſhewed his heels ſo loſt.</p>
            <p>4. A ſmall Veſſel, about 45 Tun, the Maſters name <hi>Phillip Hangare,</hi> coming upon the Coaſt of <hi>New-England,</hi> they ſuddenly ſprang a leak, and ſo foundred: There were in this poor miſcarrying Veſſel 18 Sea-men and Paſſengers; 12 of the men got into the Long-boat, and as that was ſuddenly brought to their minds in this ſurpriſe, they threw into their Boat alſo ſome ſmall matters of Proviſions, but they were wholly without fire: Theſe 12 men at that time of the year about <hi>Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elmas,</hi> (and as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid in his Voyage, <hi>Sayling was become dangerous)</hi> Sayled five hundred Leagues, and were to a Miracle preſerved all that time in this ſmall Boat, five weeks; but it pleaſed the Lord, who appears in our ſtraits moſt, to ſend them
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38362:13"/>
great relief, by cauſing ſome flying Fiſh to fall into the Boat, which they eat raw, and were unto them more acceptable than the greateſt rarities and dainties at another time; God's Providence now proving the Caterer, they catch'd a Shark, and that Ravenous Fiſh that uſes to prey upon men, now becomes a prey to theſe poor diſtreſſed Creatures; but they were glad of food in the want of fire, and have an heat in their Stomacks, to eat that raw, and digeſt at this time what would have made them ſick at other times; but alas, another want they had, was drink as well as fire, but they were forced to open the belly of this Shark, and ſuck his blood for drink; at laſt, that God who hath a deſire to the work of his own hands, gives them hopes to releaſe them out of this inſupportable miſery, by letting them come to a diſcovery of Land in the <hi>Weſt-Indies;</hi> but alas, they were ſo weak, that when they came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore, one or two of them dyed; but moſt of them lived to declare the works of the Lord. This the Author had from one of the 12 that were thus miraculouſly preſerved, but ſince caſt away at Sea.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:38362:14"/>
5. Captain <hi>Jonas Clark,</hi> of <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> going for <hi>Virginia,</hi> the Veſſel was Caſt away in a ſtrange amazing manner, about two hours before day, among the <hi>Indians</hi> where the Ship-wrackt men lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore in great fear; but three days after they thought to get their ſhip off again; to which end the Maſter, with ſome others, went into the boat, they came threeſcore Fathom from the ſhore, where there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe a great Sea, and broke in upon them; but the ſecond Sea came and turned the boat up; four men under water, all were drowned, but Captain <hi>Clark,</hi> who was kept under water by one of the men, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til his breath was gone, but then God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and ſet him at liberty from him in a moſt Miraculous way, and inabled him to ſwim to the ſhore; they that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live now, were in great ſtraits and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities, not knowing what to do, but yet ſome of their eyes were up to God; at laſt they Unanimouſly reſolve to Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, and when they had Travelled one night, and part of a day, meeting with many Swamps and thick places, ſo that all hope failed them of going along, ſo they ſtood ſtill as (wayfaring men) aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd, not knowing what courſe to take; and though before they were afraid of any
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38362:14"/>
               <hi>Indians,</hi> now they were glad to pray to the Lord for the ſight of an <hi>Indian,</hi> which in this extremity and perplexity, within half an hour the Lord was pleaſed to grant: The <hi>Indian</hi> was all alone, which was obſervable alſo; when they got to him, they asked the way to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and they did perſwade him by entreaty to go along with them, but within one hours time, he carryed them to a Town of the <hi>Indians,</hi> which did ſadly fright and amaze them; but they ſtill looked up to the Lord to help and ſave them; and at laſt they got to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſo were preſerved.</p>
            <p>This Relation the Author had from Captain <hi>Clarks</hi> own hand, a perſon of known Godlineſs and Integrity.</p>
            <p>6. The laſt Providence called to mind a ſtrange and ſtupendious paſſage of a Godly Gentlewoman, who in the firſt breaking forth of the Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> was forced to fly for her life, with ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſons in her Company; eſpecially three Children, one of them upon her Breaſt: But alas, theſe poor trembling Travellers had not gone long before they were ſtriped Naked by the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who to admiration ſpared their lives; but paſſing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38362:15"/>
on to the foot of a River, others met them and would have caſt them into the River but this Godly Woman not being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may'd, ask'd a little liberty to Pray, and as ſhe lay on frozen ground Naked, ſhe got a little reſolution not to go on her own feet to ſo unjuſt a death; upon which having call'd her, upon her reſolution, they drag'd her by the heels along the ground, with the reſt of the Company; ſhe turns upon them, and on her knees ſays, <hi>You ſhould I am ſure be Chriſtians, and men I ſee you are; in taking away our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable lives you do us a pleaſure; but know, as we never wrong'd you, nor yours, you muſt dye alſo your ſelves, and one day give an account of this Cruelty to the Judge of Heaven and Earth.</hi> Suddenly upon which, an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Prieſt ſays, <hi>Let us not take their lives, but we will put them in this Iſland of the Lake;</hi> a Boat being at the River, all the eight Naked, and without Meat, are turn'd into that Iſland, where after four days ſtaying, ſome of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany dy'd with Hunger and Cold, but not this Woman, nor any of her Children; a day after, the two Boys found the Hyde of a Beaſt which had been kill'd at the root of a Tree, which they and the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther endeavoured to caſt over them; then
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38362:15"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying upon the Snow, the next day a little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oat goes by, to whom ſhe calls for God's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake to take her out, but they refus'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing <hi>Iriſh;</hi> ſhe deſir'd a little Bread, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey ſaid they had none; ſhe begs a Coal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Fire, which ſhe obtain'd, for they had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome fewel in the Boat, and thus with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome fallen Chips, made a fire; and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oys taking a piece of the Hyde, lay'd it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon the Coals, and began to gnaw the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eather; but alas, without an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ary Divine ſupport, what could this do? Thus they lived ten days without any vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble ſupplies, and that good Woman pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt it was by Faith and Joy in God ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iv'd; nor had ſhe any Bread but Ice and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>now, nor any Drink but Water, but ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hought God put more ſubſtance in it, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound it as it were clammy. The next <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay a Boat carryed her out to the ſide of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Band-water, where yet ſhe had been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt, but that ſhe could not ſuffer to ſee her Children dye in her ſight; and therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> though the two Boys were young, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tarv'd, that they had no ſtrength) ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſſed them to go out of her ſight, under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>retence of ſeeking ſome fire; the poor Children had not gone far until they ſaw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wo or 3 great Dogs eating a man who had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een kill'd; the Children were not afraid
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38362:16"/>
of the <hi>Dogs,</hi> (who needed not fear any thing but to live in ſuch a Condition) and one of them came running, and leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon one of the Children, without doing him the leaſt hurt, and would run a little before, and then tarry until the Children come up, and ſo led them on where an Houſe whence Smoke appeared, which was an Iriſh mans, Protected by the Engliſh in <hi>Antrum,</hi> by which means they were marvellouſly pleaſed, and the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſent for, and ſuccour'd by a party from <hi>Antrum.</hi> Although this Providence be not a Sea-deliverance, yet it is a remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable preſervation from danger by Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and Hunger at Land.</p>
            <p>7. In the firſt ſetling of the <hi>Bohemi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Iſlands off the <hi>Cape</hi> of <hi>Florida,</hi> about the year 1642. there were at that preſent great troubles in the <hi>Burmoudas,</hi> one Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Sale</hi> who had been Governour the year before, comes for <hi>London,</hi> and here informing ſome of his Acquaintance and Perſons of Worth and Eſtate, how things then ſtood, they undertake fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him, and got him a Ship, and all thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neceſſary for the diſcovery of theſe Iſland<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which he had inform'd them of, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they proceeded to <hi>Burmoudas,</hi> whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they took in ſeveral Paſſengers, Captai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:38362:16"/>
               <hi>Sale</hi> being Cheif, and Captain <hi>Lane</hi> and his Family which came from <hi>London</hi> with him as his Aſſiſtant in the management of the Deſigne, ſo they in purſute of the Voyage, came to an Iſland call'd <hi>Cicatra,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he lay down in the Platts, where they could not at preſent find an Harbour. So they ſent out their <hi>Shallop</hi> upon a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, which upon Return inform'd them of a better place to Ride in.—But ſending out the <hi>Shallop</hi> again up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a diſcovery, before ſhe Return'd, there aroſe a dreadful Storm that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried her immediately upon the <hi>Rocks,</hi> and ſtav'd her, with very much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty moſt of the People were ſav'd, and ſome Proviſions. Then were they Reduc'd to very great ſtraits formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to fleſh and blood, a Barren Iſland, no inhabitants, no likelyhood of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leif, little Proviſions left; in this great ſtrait moſt of them reſolv'd to travel up to the weſter end of the Iſland and there to abide. (Captaine <hi>Lane</hi> and his Family, and his Son who was his Leiute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant) they Reſolv'd to ſeek for ſome kind of Proviſions, and ſo ſtay'd on the Iſland. But Captaine <hi>Sale</hi> and one Mr. <hi>Bounly</hi> who had been Maſter of the Ship, and ſome other Sea-men, and one Mr. <hi>Shad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:38362:17"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:38362:17"/>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:38362:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:38362:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:38362:19"/>
in all eight, Reſolv'd to go to <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia,</hi> and took what Proviſions they could get, which was one <hi>Shark;</hi> but before they made to the Land they were in very great wants; For from this Iſland from whence they departed to <hi>Virginia,</hi> was three hundred Leagues: in their now great Extreamity, Providence car'd for them, ſo that they got another <hi>Shark,</hi> and were glad to eat him Raw. They were a 11 days going to <hi>Virginia,</hi> and the <hi>Boat</hi> a very little one, that they could ſcarcely Steer in her for fear of danger. Yet the Lord in this deep Diſtreſs, made his Arm bare for their Salvation, and brought them ſafe to a place call'd <hi>Nuſe mum;</hi> to one Mr. <hi>Richard Brunkets</hi> Houſe, where they were curtiouſly En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd; and after the Relation upon what account they were put to theſe Hardſhips and Neceſſities, Captain <hi>Sale</hi> had a Veſſel provided laden with ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, to go for <hi>Cicatra,</hi> to Relieve thoſe they had left there in ſuch Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, and they arriv'd there. And O now what Comfort muſt this be, after ſuch long wiſhing and gradual Dying, to ſee that there was now Hopes of Life brought to them; but ſeveral of them were ſtarv'd to Death before their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38362:19"/>
Arrival. Captain <hi>Lane</hi> is now ſent to fetch ſome Proviſions who had been in unſpeakable Extreamity. He came down in a little <hi>Boat,</hi> his Son alſo the Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and two Servants, but when they had gotten in their Proviſion, and going home with hopes of a new Life; Behold, the ſtupendious providence of God, all of a ſudden Death creeps in and Arreſts them. For in a narrow place where the Tyde runs ſwiftly, the <hi>Boat</hi> is ſunk, all are drowned but one man, who car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the deſolate Widdow the ſad Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what an unwelcome Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger this was you may eaſily conjecture; about three months after arrived a Veſſel to them (the maſter of her my Author,) and ſo Mrs. <hi>Lane,</hi> her Son and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Maid Servant and Man Servant, where all brought up about forty miles, where they were entertain'd by my Author for ſix weeks, and gave an account of ſome notable paſſages of Gods Providence in preſerving them. Worthy never to be forgotten! Her Husband and the men went out to ſee what they could get for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> every Day, and they had for the moſt part juſt for the Day, and ſhe told my Author that ſhe as a tender hearted Mother would lay ſomething
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38362:20"/>
by for her younger Children; but ſhe obſerv'd that the next Day they never got any thing.</p>
            <p>And thus Providence train'd them up in the School of Faith; but further ſhe gave an account of one Remarkable thing, In the laſt day of the week, upon a time it proved a very ſtormy Day, and they being abroad a hunting for ſome ſupport, could get nothing. The Husband and Son comes home very much troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and the men that were gon into the Woods they could get nothing; and they being very much troubled, one took up a Reſolution not to come home, knowing their Captain would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to go and hunt on the Lords Day; on the other hand they thought he would wounder what was become of them, and fear leſt evil had befallen them; ſo they alter their Reſolution to come home, but empty of any Reliefe; this very Evening before the Sabbath in this perplexety of thoughts, there flys over their Heads three gray <hi>Geeſe;</hi> a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it was for ſuch <hi>Geeſe</hi> that were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeen before nor after. O ſays ſhe to her Husband, that we had ſome of them againſt to morrow! obſerving they lighted in a Bottome, ſhe acquaints her
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38362:20"/>
Husband, he ſays they have no ſhot left. O ſays ſhe, here is a Porrenger, melt it or cut it into peices, which he did for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, and charged his Peice, and at the firſt ſhot kill'd them all,—Theſe things, and many more my Author had from her own Mouth, after her marvellous Preſervation. O that men would Praiſe the Lord, for his wonderful Works to the Children of Men.</p>
            <p>8. We have a very wonderful Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance recorded, an honeſt poor man in <hi>Maulden</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> one <hi>Gregory Crow,</hi> who with his man and boy, was in his Boat go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to fetch Fullers-Earth; but by the way meeting with a Stom his Boat was driven upon a banck of ſand, and there ſunk; The men were glad to hang upon the Maſt, but poor <hi>Crow</hi> ſeeing his New-Teſtament in the water, which he prized highly, caught it up, and took it into his Boſom; the tyde being gone, they were left upon the ſand, at leaſt ten miles from land; now in this great Diſtreſſe they made their Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers to the Lord, that he would ſend ſome means of Deliverance, For now within half an hour it would be flood, but in this little time before Flood, they found a Cheſt wherein was five pounds ſix Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38362:21"/>
eight pence, but honeſt <hi>Crow</hi> caſt it into the Sea again ſaying, <hi>If the Lord will pleaſe to ſave our lives he will provide us a little food;</hi> and ſo they went again up the Maſt, where they to Admiration hung by the Arms and Leggs for ten hours toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, only the Boy was ſo weary, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the Waves that he fell off, and was drowned; now their fears encreaſe upon them, and they know not what to do. But <hi>Crow</hi> adviſes his man to cut down the Maſt and when the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood comes again, to fit upon it, and ſo, ſayes he, it may pleaſe God to drive us to ſome Ship; this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel was taken, they commit themſelves to God upon this Maſt, and thus continu'd <hi>Tueſday</hi> Night, <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> and <hi>Wedneſday</hi> Night; in which time the man was ſo tir'd out with Hunger, Watching, and Cold, that he dyed; now was <hi>Crow</hi> left alone in this ſad and deplorable Condition, who pray'd now the more earneſtly for ſome Succor and Relief, but durſt not Sleep, leſt the Sea ſhould beat him off the Maſt; and when this diſtreſſ'd miſerable object was almoſt ſpent, his fleſh ſodden with Sea water, and his eyes almoſt cloſed up with the Salt, now in his Extremity the Lord makes it his opportunity, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eps in by his Providence, perſents a Ship go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:38362:21"/>
for <hi>Antwerp:</hi> (obſerve here the Finger of God:) The Wind not being favourable was driven out of the way, and eſpying ſomething a far off in the Sea, but ſuppoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to be ſome Fiſher-boy ſteer'd from it. <hi>Crow</hi> ſeeing this, held up his Cap and ſhaked it over his head, whereby at length they were mov'd to go to him, and ſo they took him in; when he came into the Ship, being half dead, careful of his New Teſtament, he pluckt it out of his Boſome and gave it to ſome to dry. They in the Ship were careful of him, and with great difficulty recover'd him, and carryed him with them to <hi>Antwerp,</hi> where the fame of his being miraculouſly deliver'd, drew ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to ſee him, and relieve him with neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. <hi>Fox's Book of Martyrs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>9. A Ship of <hi>Holland</hi> being driven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her will, came to a Place call'd <hi>Zembla,</hi> where the Pole is elevated Seventy Six degrees; they among many delays, and great dangers, ſcarce reach'd the Aurange Iſlands; for now they were ſet faſt in a Conſolidated body of continu'd Ice, which threatn'd them every moment; at laſt being reduc'd to their ultimate hope, they reſolve to return the ſame way they came, but now they find the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38362:22"/>
Ship quite frozen up, not far from ſhore, and now they think they ſhould winter in <hi>Zembla</hi> and waite for a better Seaſon, wherefore taking out Boards and Plancks, they built for themſelves, and their Stuffe, a poor ſhelter, and by a good Providence, the Tide had thrown up a good quantity of Timber, they not knowing from whence it came, it proved a great advantage to them during their abode; here they had continual fights with Bears, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times were driven away with making great out-crys, other whiles with Shot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they found their fleſh unwholeſome for food. (For in this place the Maritine wild Beaſts, are the food to the wild Beaſts of the land) the fat of the Bears they made uſe of to burn for lights in the night; theſe poor creatures were at laſt, after all other Humane Benefits, left by the Sun, in this Barren Country, and left amongſt none but wild Beaſts: The vaſt Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Snow, with great difficulty they remove, leſt the Habitation ſhould be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelm'd, and if at any time they went forth, their jawes were ſo benum'd they could ſcarce recover their former heat; now the Bears in the dark, being dull of fight did not venture out to diſturbe them, but multitudes of Foxes, which
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:38362:22"/>
they took in Traps, and made of them both Victuals and Rayment; and yet after all theſe dangers and difficultys God preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them, though indeed ſome of them dyed, they were 12 of them: The chief of them was one <hi>Jacob Hamskerk,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned afterwards to <hi>Amſterdam.</hi> Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ius <hi>in his Annalls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>10. In the year 1616 a flemming named <hi>Pickman,</hi> well known in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for the art he had in getting out of the Sea, the great Guns of that <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet, that was forced upon the Coaſt of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> in the year 1588. coming from <hi>Dronthem</hi> in <hi>Norway,</hi> laden with Boards, was overtaken by a Calm, during which, the current of the Sea carryed him on a Rock or a little Iſland to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the extremity of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where he was in ſome danger of being caſt away; to avoide a wrack, he commanded ſome of his men to go into the ſhallop, and to tow off the Ship: theſe having done ſo, would needs go upon a certain Rock to ſeek for eggs, but as ſoon as they were got up into it, they eſpy'd a man, whence they imagine there were others lay there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and that he had made an Eſcape thither to avoid ſome Pirats which might Surprize their Ship, ſo that they made all
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38362:23"/>
the haſt they could to the Shallop, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to the Ship; but the Calme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing, and the current of the Sea driving the Veſſel againſt the Iſland, they were forc'd to get into the Long-boat and Tow her off again; the man they ſaw before, was in the mean time come to the brink of the Iſland, and made ſignes to them with his hands, entreating them to come nearer; and falling on his Knees, and joyning his Hands together, he beg'd Relief from them; at laſt coming near the Iſland, they ſaw ſomething more like a Ghoſt than a living Perſon, a body ſtark Naked, black, hairy, of a meager and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Countenance, hollow and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorted Eyes, which raiſed ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion in them, that they proffer'd to take him into their Boat; at laſt with ſome difficulty they took him in; they found upon the Iſland no Graſs nor Trees, nothing for Food, nor any ſhelter, but the ruins of a boat, wherewith he had made himſelf an Hut, under which he might be cover'd from Rain and injuries of the Weather; when they came to ask him who he was, and how he came into that un-inhabited place, he reply'd to them he was an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man, and that a year before he was to go from <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:38362:23"/>
to <hi>Dublin</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> in the Paſſage-Boat, and that they were taken by a <hi>French-</hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, who by a Storm that immediately aroſe, was forc'd to let go the Paſſage-Boat, left us to the mercy of the Waves, which carryed us between <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> into the main Sea, expecting to be caſt away every minute, as at laſt we were: For the Bark being ſplit againſt the Rock, where you took me in, I eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with one of my Comrades into the Iſland, in a more wretched condition than if ſwallow'd up by the Sea; who then had been deliver'd out of the Extremities we were in for want of meat and drink; of ſome of the boards of our Boat we made the Hutt you ſaw, and we took ſome Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mews which we ſet a drying in the Wind and Sun, and ſo eat them raw; we found alſo in the crevices of the Rock, by the Sea-ſide, ſome Eggs: Thus were we kept from ſtarving; but what we thought moſt inſupportable, was Thirſt; for there was no Water, but what fell from Heaven; we liv'd thus ſix weeks, comforting one another, and finding ſome eaſe in our common misfortune, till that being left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, it began to grow inſupportable to me; for one day, awaking in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and miſſing my Comrade, I fell into
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38362:24"/>
ſuch a Deſpair, that I had ſome though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of caſting my ſelf head-long, and ſo put a final period to that Affliction, whereof I had but endur'd the one half while I had a Friend ſuffering with me: I know not what became of him, but I am of that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion that he fell into the Sea, ſeeking for Eggs; I left with him my Knife, with which we kill'd the Sea-Doggs, and the Mews, upon which we lived; ſo I was forc'd to get out of my Hut a great Nail, which I made a ſhift to ſharpen upon the Rock, that it ſerv'd me for a Knife: I was alſo forc'd to lade a little ſtick, with a little Sea-dogg fat, and put it out of a crevice of my Hut, and ſo got ſome Mews to keep me from ſtarving: I liv'd in this condition and ſolitude Eleven Months, and was reſolv'd to end my days in it, when God ſent you to deliver me out of the greateſt miſery that ever man was in, and this Sea-man after this miſery and miraculous preſervation, liv'd to return to <hi>England.</hi> Ambaſadors <hi>Travels.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Remarkable Providence of God in wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preſerving of Eleven or Thirteen poor diſtreſſed mens lives.</head>
               <p>11. In the year 68. a Ketch Sailed from <hi>Salom</hi> in <hi>New-England</hi> for the <hi>Barbadoes;</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:38362:24"/>
and when they came into the Latitude of 35. it began to look like foul weather, ſo they took in their Top-ſail, and becauſe it was towards night, they ſtruck down the Main ſail, and Rafed it; and all this time there was but a little wind (which was remarkable, if the enſuing ſtory be obſerv'd) but ſtill it looked like bad wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo they ſent up one to Tallow tho Maſt, and made no great haſt to ſet Sayll; the man at the Top thinks he ſees ſome black thing float upon the Sea, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon it very fixtly, he conceives it to be a Boat, and ſo calls to the men below, ſo they haſten'd to hoiſe Sayl and make towards it; and when they came to them, there was a Long-boat with a 11 or 13 men, (my Author could not abſolutely remember the juſt number) which poor diſtreſſed Creatures, had been bound for <hi>Virginia;</hi> and the ſhip in which they were, prov'd very Leaky, and ſo exceedingly encreas'd, that in a very little time, ſhe was ready to ſink; ſo all hands haſten'd to get out the boat, but the Maſter ſtept into the Cabbin to fetch a Compaſs, and took ſome Canvas, a Sayl-needle and twine which he thought might be uſeful to them in their Need and Extremity, but while <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his poor induſtrious man was endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:38362:25"/>
to be uſeful to ſome other mens lives, he was in danger to loſe his own; for the boat was put off, and the ſhip ſinking, ſo he crys to them in this diſtreſs, <hi>if they would leave him, and let him there Periſh;</hi> ſo they came back, and took him in; they had in their boat a Capſtone-bar, which they made uſe of for a Maſt, and the piece of Canvas for a Sayl, and ſo Sayled afore the wind, and had no kind of Food; and now comes dreadful and inexpreſſible di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs upon them, making them wiſh for death it ſelf to give them a deliverance, now all hopes of Relief fail'd them; thus they continu'd five days, ſome grew Lame, others Feeble, and all much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearten'd by deſpair of Life; and now upon the 6th. day, they had concluded to caſt Lotts for their lives, who ſhould dye to preſerve others; and they put their Reſolution into Execution, and that poor Creature, upon whom the Lott fell, begs for time; but alas, what will a Reprieve be in this caſe, where there is no hope of Relief; but O what difficult work is it to dye? what a ſtrait was here? Live he could not, and Dye he could not; well, a little time is defer'd, and behold a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-working God appears now for him, and for them all; before night, they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpy'd
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:38362:25"/>
this Ketch, which rais'd them all to Admiration; but they had fears in this diſtreſs, that the Ketch did not ſee them; but when they perceiv'd the Ketch made to them, O what a new life did it put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe dying men; ſo they all got ſafe Aboard: And ſee here the goodneſs of God: In one hour after there aroſe a moſt dreadful Storm which continu'd for forty hours, and all of them ſafely Arriv'd at <hi>Barbadoes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Maſters name of the Ketch was <hi>Thomas Woodberry</hi> of <hi>Salom.</hi> This the Author had from a very known perſon of Integrity and Godlineſs, now living at <hi>Salom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>12. In the year 1606. in the Wars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Netherlands</hi> and the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> upon the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ocean, fell out this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable and remarkable action, taken notice of by <hi>Grotius,</hi> in his Annals of the Low-Country Wars. Admiral <hi>Hauteen</hi> being ſent to intercept the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet, coming from <hi>America</hi> and the <hi>Indies,</hi> he had with him four and twenty Veſſels; but of theſe, ſix were beaten back by Tempeſts; ſoon after <hi>Fraſciardo,</hi> with eight great Gallions, having a proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Gale, fell upon them unprovided,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38362:26"/>
and e're they were aware; but the Galleys that were with him, not being driven by the Wind, kept by the ſhore; but one of them being grappl'd with a ſhip of <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that was next the Admiral, ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted the reſt, that as ſoon as they ſaw it, they in the very beginning of the Night, Retreated with all haſt. <hi>Hauteen</hi> thus left by his Companions, being a man of an Undaunted ſpirit, for two whole days did not leave off the Fight, though moſt of his men were in that time loſt; but with his torne ſhip, caſting off all fear of danger, protracted the Victory; but after he ſaw no hopes of Relief, and that the Waves pour'd in upon him, that none of them might come alive into the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies hands, at once they Unanimouſly agreed upon a Reſolute and Terrible action: For kneeling down upon their Knees, they like dying, but deſperate men, beg of God, that he would pleaſe to pardon in that they ſought to ſhun the Mockeries and Cruelties of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> by that ſad and lamentable death; ſo they ſet fire to the Gun powder, by which blow threeſcore men were kill'd, two half dead lived a little while, being taken by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> with wonder, beholding their dreadful Countenances, and their words,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:38362:26"/>
with their ſtrange Reſolution and Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy in Death.</p>
               <p>13. In the year 1607. about the time when the Plantations of <hi>Virginia</hi> began to be a little ſettled by King <hi>James,</hi> ſome <hi>Britains</hi> went to <hi>Guyana,</hi> but a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Sedition aroſe in the Voyage, and the Ship being loſt, part of the Company remained in the Iſland, where continually vexing the <hi>Barbarians</hi> with their unkind uſage, they, at laſt, were ſet upon by War as Enemies; by force of which, and the want of Victuals, they committed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Sea in a Boat made only of an Hollow Tree; there theſe poor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Creatures were toſſed with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Tempeſts, betwixt Deſpair and Hope of Life; but at laſt they were driven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Rocks, after great miſery endured by them in their little Boat for Ten days together; and now their danger was leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſen'd, for here they muſt fall into the hands of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who pardon'd them, in regard they came not to thoſe Parts of their own accord, but by the ſtreſs of Weather. Thus were theſe poor diſtreſſed Men ſaved and preſerved, when all hope of being ſaved was taken away.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:38362:27"/>
14. The <hi>Phoenix</hi> Frigot, in the time when Captain <hi>Wheſton</hi> Commanded her, and Mr. <hi>May</hi> was Maſter, being Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to carry ſome Perſons of Quality from <hi>Rye</hi> to <hi>Deep</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> the Captain and ſeveral of the Gentlemen that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the Frigot was Aſhore; the Captain ſends the Long-boat Aboard, and Order'd the Frigot to weigh and come to ſayl, and ſtand too and fro off in the Bay, and he would come out in his Pinnis; and the Gentlemen that was with him, were namely <hi>Sunebank Giles</hi> his Chyrurgion, Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> his Chaplain, Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> his Barbar and Gentleman, Mr. <hi>Richards,</hi> and ſome three more Gentlemen Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madoes, <hi>Abraham Car</hi> Coxſwain, and about 12 Seamen for his Crew, that ſet out of <hi>Rye,</hi> and croſſed the Bay to meet the Frigot under Sayl; and when they came near, being a good way a-head, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the Frigot to keep her way, and not to come a playſe for her, which ſhe did with a freſh Top-ſail Gail of Wind, till ſhe came up with the Pinnis, and then the Coxen would a-laid her Aboard of the Larboard-ſide; but the Captain ſuppoſing himſelf far enough a-head, Commanded him to ſhout a-head of her, and lay her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board of the Starboard-ſide, which he aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:38362:27"/>
to do, the Ship giving a ſaw, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving freſh way, the Pinnis was not paſt, but the Cotwater of the Ship cut the Pinnis in the middle, and run right over, that ſhe lay in a moment of time in 100 pieces, and all the Men floating for their lives; in the interim of which time, with a Cry, they gave a leap, in which leap, the Captain catcht hold o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Railes of the Head, Mr. <hi>Richards</hi> on the Captain's heels, Mr. <hi>Giles</hi> the Chyrurgion on <hi>Richard</hi>'s heels, Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> on <hi>Giles</hi>'s heels, and ſome other perſon on his; ſo that with that ſpring, or leap, no leſs than 4 or 5 pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntially catcht about one the others heels or middle, as Boys when at play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Truſs; and in hoyſting in the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, they preſerved 4 or 5 more with him; the Coxen ſunk down, and brought ſome of the Tallow of the Lower part of the ſhip on his cloaths, and came up again at the Stern, where he was taken up by the Seamen; ſome by ſwiming, others by the aſſiſtance of the Oar, and pieces of the Boat, by God's bleſſing kept them from drowning, till the Long-boat took them all up, except the Captain's Barber Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> whom it ſeems had ſunk, its thought his laſt time; but Providence ſo order'd it, that the Man in the main
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38362:28"/>
Channel having the hand Lead, there fell a chrockle in the dipſey-Line, and in that very interim, the Lead fell in the very place where the Barber was ſunk, and the chinckle of the Line fell about the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers Fingers, hitcht about his Ring, and ſo providentially faſten'd it ſelf, ſo that as the Man in the Sceanes haling up his Lead, found it to come heavier than it uſed to do; admiring, at laſt up comes the Barber faſtned in the chinkle by his Ring, which the Spectators amazed at, immediately took hold of him, and pulled him into the Frigot, with his Eyes fixed, and Teeth ſet, and little appearance of Life; but by the bleſſing of God on the immediate means uſed, and care of him, he ſoon came to himſelf, and recovered; ſo that notwithſtanding this ſhrewd diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, which might have proved fatal to all, or moſt of them, yet there was not one Man of them all miſcarry'd, but was recover'd to their health again, as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of God's Mercy. For truth of this, many of the Men are alive at this day; the Chyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rgion now living in <hi>Grays-Inn-Lane;</hi> and at the very interim of time I was then aboard the ſaid Frigot, and was not only an Eye-ſpectator, but an Inſtrument to help in preſerving of ſome
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38362:28"/>
of them, and therefore may Aver it to be Truth. <hi>Ezekiel Fog.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>15. About Ten years ago, in the Iſland of <hi>Barbados,</hi> there did arrive one Mr. <hi>John Blackleach</hi> (from New <hi>England)</hi> a very honeſt Man, who gave account, that in his then Voyage, his Son being Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Veſſel, and himſelf Merchant, their Men at Sea did Mutiny, at which occaſion he and his Son was forced to ſtand on their Guard for ſome time, caſting his care on the Lord: But whilſt under this trouble, being in the Long-Reach, in or near the Latitude of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badoes,</hi> they all did ſee a Great Ship which ſtood toward them; and while they were Looking on her, to ſee how faſt ſhe came towards them (ſhe being pretty near) vaniſh'd away, which ſtruck the Men with Great Fear, and made them humble themſelves to the Good Old Man, and deſired his Prayers for them.</p>
               <p>16. In the Month of <hi>November,</hi> 1669, the Ship Proſperous of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ailed from thence, being bound for <hi>Galloway</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> but was forced into <hi>Bruts-Bay</hi> in <hi>Cornwal,</hi> where the Ship brake in pieces, ſix Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:38362:29"/>
being Drowned, others wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully caſt on Shore and bruiſed; amongſt the reſt <hi>John Denny</hi> (a Skinner of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol)</hi> was caſt a Shore by a Great Sea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much bruiſed and almoſt Dead; and was by ſome ſtript naked, and laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the other Dead Folk that were taken up, being only cover'd with ſome Straw or Rubbiſh. But by Providence, an Old Man looking on the Dead People, did perceive ſome Life in the ſaid <hi>Denny,</hi> and the Lord open'd his heart, that he ſtript himſelf of his own Shirt and ſome Cloaths, and put on him, and took him from amongſt the Dead: through his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and Love, by God's bleſſing, the ſaid <hi>Denny</hi> is now well and liveth at <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol.</hi> This my Author had from <hi>John Denny</hi>'s own Mouth.</p>
               <p>17. In the Year 1671, I being at <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> I oft went to ſee an Acquaintance of mine, one <hi>Abraham Darby,</hi> a ſober honeſt Man, a Maſter of a Veſſel, who relates the following Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which he atteſteth to be Truth. That ſome few years ago, he the ſaid <hi>Darby</hi> being Maſter of a ſmall Ketch, was bound from <hi>Barbadoes</hi> to <hi>Virginia,</hi> he having an Iriſh Woman, a Servant, on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Board, to be deliver'd in <hi>Virginia,</hi> but
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:38362:29"/>
ſhe was a vile Perſon, and having often of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, at laſt was puniſh'd, for which ſhe ſaid they ſhould not carry her to <hi>Virginia,</hi> tho the Wind was very fair, and carried them in ſounding of the <hi>Capps</hi> of <hi>Virginia:</hi> That they had bent one Cable to the Anckor, thinking ſoon to get in; but ſhe ſtill ſaid they ſhould not: then the Wind ſprang up of a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, in a meer fret, which forced them many days off, and their Proviſions near ſpent (it being, if I miſtake not, in <hi>Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h)</hi> then the Wind came fair again, a freſh Gaile, and they before it, in hopes to gain their paſſage; but on a ſudden there came a Great Sea that caſt the Veſſel on her ſide (ſhe having but little beſide Ballaſt in her) that her Goods and things in hold ſhifteth. But it pleaſed God they clapt the Helm a weather, and ſhe wore, and all hands as could in the Hold brought her to rights, and the Wind continued fair till they came near the place that it took them ſhort before, and then took them as before, that they were forc'd off again for many days, having then but two or three pieces of Beefe, and no Bread, nor (I think) above a Gallon of freſh Water: But after ſome time the Wind came fair, they making Sail to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:38362:30"/>
get back, it being fine weather, there came a great <hi>Sea</hi> and laid her down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and carried her Maſt away, and a part of the Partners that hould the Maſt, that as ſhe lay on one ſide, the <hi>Sea</hi> ruſh'd into her; but the Maſter with his Bed and Rug ſtopt the force, till it pleaſed God they had ſhifted the things in the hould and brought her to rights again, (now theſe poor Souls were left as a Wrack in the Ocean, and neither Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als nor Drink, but ſtrong Water and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, to help them) but finding a Spar or Oars, in the hould, made ſhift to get out a ſmal Sail (I had like to have omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that whilſt they had any Food, they would have given this wicked Woman a part, but ſhe would not Eat any thing) then it pleaſed God to ſend a fine Gale, and they got on the Coſt of <hi>New-England,</hi> and ſounding, round about forty Fathom Water, and very calme; then they chopt to an Anckor there, and that Night got two or three Fiſh, wherewith they Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed themſelves (but the Woman would not Eat) but could get no more: and finding a fine Gale, weighed Anckor, and thought to have got with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Cape-Cod,</hi> not being far of; but the Wind came freſh againſt them, and drove
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:38362:30"/>
them off again to Sea, and then 'twas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alm; and about that time the Woman <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad faſted about 21 Days, and yet could Curſe and Damn, and ſay, She ſhould not go Aſhore; but that Night the Maſter and ſome others being on the Deck, ſpied a Great Black Thing Riſe out of the Sea, to their thinking, much bigger than the Ketch, the Sea being Light all about, and the Woman in the Hold made a Great Noyſe; and when ſhe had given a Great Screach or Groan, this Great Black Thing Vaniſh'd, the Water ſeeming like Fire all round, and made a Great Sea and Noiſe: And when the Men came to them ſelves, they looking for the Woman, found her Dead; and after they had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ung her over-Board, they had a brave Wind and Weather, and got ſafe to <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>18. At <hi>New-England,</hi> in the year 1671, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpoke with <hi>John Grafting</hi> of <hi>Sal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m,</hi> and others of good Repute, who told me, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ong before the ſaid <hi>Grafting</hi> ſuffered Shipwrack amongſt the Leward Iſlands, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Name of the Place I forget) the Ship or Ketch being broken to pieces, himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Mate, and one or two were caſt with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Sea aſhore amongſt the Rocks moſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:38362:31"/>
wonderfully, not knowing of each other till by Providence they met amongſt the Rocks, it being an Iſland without Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants (if I miſtake not) and they bruiſed yet the Lord provided for them in a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful manner, and not only there, but in their getting off that place, and bringin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them ſafe to their Friends and Relation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Salem</hi> in <hi>New-England;</hi> where Praiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was returned to the Lord, who wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preſerves the Children of Men. hope this ere long will be enlarged from the Party himſelf.</p>
               <p>19. I being well Acquainted with on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Jeffery Howard</hi> a Marriner, who is a Man of Good Repute, he told me as followeth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> That about Twelve or Fourteen year<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſince, he was coming through the City o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Salisbury,</hi> he was looking on the Stree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rivers, and ſpies ſomething move on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Water; but looking earneſtly ſaw it to have Life, ſteps in and got it out, and found it to be a Man-child, only inrapt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it came into the World from its Mother and it was put to Nurſe, and now is become a fine Youth.</p>
               <p>20. At <hi>Briſtol,</hi> a place well known, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many years ago, a Man fell into the River<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:38362:31"/>
near about the marſh, and not being ſeen, was carri'd down with the tide ſomeway; and, I think, could not ſwim, but lay as dead on the water, driving with the tide, but by providence, ſome being in the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow going to work, or coming from the <hi>Lymekils,</hi> Being by the water ſide play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a Spaniel, ſaw ſomthing floating, ſlung in things to make the dog fetch it; and the dog accordingly took hold of the man by the cloaths, and brought him a ſhore; and finding ſome ſymptoms of Life, took care of him; and he came to Life, and dwels in New-<hi>Briſtol.</hi> This I had from the Spectators.</p>
               <p>21. In the year 1671 one Mr. <hi>Savage, Maſter</hi> of the Society Ketch, bound from <hi>Briſtol</hi> to <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> met on the coaſt of <hi>N. E.</hi> the Ship called the <hi>George</hi> of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> being in diſtreſs, ſpake with them; the ſhip having ſprang a lcak, their men tired and ſpent with Pumping; the Maſter and all his Company went on Board the Ketch with ſpeed, and ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſhip ſunk.</p>
               <p>This I had from Mr. <hi>Savage</hi> and other Paſſengers with him, who affirmed it to be truth. <hi>David Fogg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:38362:32"/>
22. Captain <hi>John Trankmore,</hi> Commander of a Ship belonging to <hi>Apſom,</hi> near <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> in one of his Voyages of late years, being at Sea in a dark night, and foul wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, fell foul of another ſhip unexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, not then knowing what each other were, but a Sea parting them again; in the interim Captain <hi>Trankmore's</hi> ſhip, ſhipt a great Sea which waſh'd the ſaid <hi>Trank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi> over-board; and another Sea, caſt, or hove him into the other ſhip, which fell out to be an <hi>Engliſh-</hi>man, bound for <hi>Plymouth:</hi> Thus in the dark, the Wind and Sea parts the ſaid ſhip, without having knowledge of each other, Captain <hi>Trankmore</hi> concluding that his own ſhip was foundred and all his men Loſt, and God had wrought a wonder of mercy in his Preſervation; but ſo it fell out, that one <hi>Samuel Snytal,</hi> who was his Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, had obtain'd ſuch knowledge of the Art of Navigation, and his Maſter being gone, and as they ſuppos'd drown'd, being waſh'd over-board, was neceſſitated to improve his skill, and by Gods bleſſing, he carry'd the ſhip ſafe home to <hi>Apſom,</hi> where Arriving, although they had made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> good Voyaye, yet the ſorrow for the loſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Maſter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at up all the Comfort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Smiles a Proſperous Voyage otherwiſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:38362:32"/>
would have made; but ſo Providence or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd it, that about the ſame time, three or four days after, the other ſhip Arrives ſafe in <hi>Plymouth;</hi> where the ſaid <hi>Trank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi> Landed, very ſorrowful and dejected, having (as he ſuppoſed) loſt his Ship (wherein he was deeply concern'd as an Adventurer himſelf) and all his Men; as he was in the Morning walking on the Hope at <hi>Plymouth</hi> very Dejectedly, he Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially meets with one of his Executors, or <hi>Apſom</hi> Neighbours, who looks him in the Face with Aſtoniſhment, knowing him well, and yet believing the Report of his being dead, or loſt, in amaze Salutes him with theſe Expreſſions; <hi>What, Captain</hi> Trankmore? who replyes, <hi>A poor Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; having loſt my Ship richly Laden, and after a good Voyage, with all my Men, not a ſoul ſaved but my ſelf</hi> Whom, by a Miracle, God wrought Salvation for, (as before-Recited) giving the Gentleman, his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, an account of the Providence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him; when, after a little pauſe, his Friend imbraces him, and with admiring of the Providence, bids him be of good heart, for his Ship and all his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was well and ſafe Arrived at <hi>Apſom;</hi> for his Man <hi>Samuel Snytal</hi> had brought her ſafe home, and all the Sorrow
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:38362:33"/>
and cry there, was for the loſs of him. Which reply, ſtruck the ſaid <hi>Trankmore</hi> in as much amaze on the other hand, being almoſt Incredulous of truth, till his Friend poſſitively affirming it, and then conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own Mercy, ſaw, and was made ſenſible, there was no Mercy too great for God to work, and from thence took heart, recovering himſelf, went home rejoycing, where he found his expectation anſwer'd, and a wellcome given him by all perſons with him concern'd.</p>
               <p>For the truth, I have heard it acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd by Captain <hi>Trankmore</hi>'s own mouth at my Houſe in <hi>Briſtol;</hi> and farther, the ſame <hi>Snytal</hi> was my Predeceſſor's Son, and I have heard his Mother-in-law ſpeak of it to ſeveral, and hath affirmed it to me for a truth.</p>
               <p>23. The <hi>Briſtol</hi> Frigot, when Captain <hi>Fenn</hi> was Commander, being in the Straits in Chace of Captain <hi>Popoctiene,</hi> a Spaniſh Knight of <hi>Malto,</hi> who at that time our Squadron took and brought Priſoner to the <hi>Tower;</hi> in purſuit of which Chace, the Wind began to riſe, the Captain Commands preſently to get the Top-gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant ſails abroad; and the Yards being not then Aloaft, three Men run up preſently,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:38362:33"/>
where one ſtood on the top of the Shroud, under the Main Top-maſt-croſs-trees, a ſecond ſtood a top of the Croſs-trees, and the other ſtood by the Top-gallant-maſt on the Cape, at the Main Top-maſt-head; all expediting their work in getting the Top-gallant-ſail abroad; at which time the wind freſhen'd, and carry'd our Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>top-maſt by the board; in which diſaſter the Man that was lowermoſt, and leaſt in danger, fell over-board and was drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and the other two which were in Greateſt danger (one of their Names was <hi>Roger Dennis,</hi> under the Denomination of a Quaker) inſtead of being bruis'd and their bones broken all to pieces, which the eye of Reaſon could not otherwiſe imagine by ſuch a fall; they both fell for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward upon the Bunt of the Main-courſe, and one catches hold of the Main Bunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, and the other of the Leech-lines, and ſlacke of a bowling. and ſo both comes down to the Deck, and neither of them in the leaſt prejudic'd.</p>
               <p>For the truth of this, my Author was then Aboard the ſaid Frigot, and was an Eye-witneſs of this Providence.</p>
               <p>24. An Account of two Ships bound for New-found-Land, from ſome part in the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:38362:34"/>
Weſt of <hi>England,</hi> who by diſtreſs of Weather loſt Company; ſome days after being fair weather, one of the Ships ſprang a Leak, and foundred in the Sea, where every Soul periſh'd, except one Old Man, who had laſht himſelf on the main Hatch, and committed himſelf to the Mercy o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Sea and God's Providence, where he was floating three days and three nights; in which time, about the middle of the ſecond day, the Devil aſſuming the ſhape of a Mare-maid, ſtarts up before him, and bids him be of good heart, for, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he would but make a Contract with him he would ingage a Deliverance for him in 24 hours; the Old Man being ſenſible it was the Devil, and doubtleſs, having been a proving of his heart to God, as the Circumſtance of Providence he was under more immediately called for, found in himſelf a renewed ſtrength put into him, inabling him to hold up his head, and looking the Tempter in the Face; Replyes, <hi>Ah Satan, if thou canſt propheſy deliverance for me; know, my God in whom I truſt, will deliver me without thy help; but however, know, I will not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to thy wiles, therefore avoid Satan, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void;</hi> ſo immediately he Vaniſh'd, and appear'd no more to him: But ſo it fell
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:38362:34"/>
out, the other Ship being at that time in the ſame Peril or Latitude, that Night<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Cabbin-Boy Dreams a Dream, that ſuch a Ship thereabouts was Foundred, and every Soul loſt, except ſuch an Old Man, naming his Name, who was ſaved on a piece of a Ship, and floating in the Sea; which Dream, the Boy in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confidently tells to the Company and his Maſter; at laſt, the Boy began to ſhew more Confidence, affirming it, as if it muſt be true; inſomuch, he receiv'd ſome Checks from his Maſter; but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, at laſt, the Boy grew ſo reſtleſs, that he, running up from one Maſt to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, ſometimes at Fore-top-maſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, and then on the Main-top-maſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, looking abroad, that at laſt, crying out aloud; <hi>Alow there, I ſee him, I ſee him under our Lee-bon;</hi> thus confidently affirming it, ſome of the Men ſtept up, and ſpy'd ſomething at a diſtance no big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than a Crow to appearance, floating, and adviſed the Maſter of it, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently commanded the Helm to be born up, and ſtood away to it; and when they came near, found it to be the Old Man, as the Boy ſaid; ſo they hoyſt out their Boat, and took him in, who then was ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and almoſt ſpent; but by the care of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:38362:35"/>
the Maſter and the Chyrurgion, with God's Bleſſing, recover'd, and gave a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal account of his Misfortune, and yet wonderful deliverance; together with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan's Temptation as before recited; which Ship, in due time, Arriv'd ſafe at her Port in <hi>New-found-Land,</hi> where this Man was well Landed a-ſhore.</p>
               <p>For Confirmation, I had this, and heard it related at my Father's Houſe in <hi>Salom</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> by Mr. <hi>John Blackledge</hi> a Merchant, who is a Perſon of a ſober life, and in Fellowſhip there, who then came from <hi>New-found-land,</hi> and did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that he ſpake with the Man himſelf, whom God wrought this wonderful deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance for, he being then at <hi>New-found-Land</hi> when the ſaid Ship Arriv'd there, and the Man went firſt aſhore.</p>
               <p>25. <hi>Anno Chriſti.</hi> 1630. <hi>May</hi> the firſt, the <hi>Moſcory</hi> Merchants of <hi>London</hi> ſent a Ship called the <hi>Salutation</hi> of <hi>London</hi> for <hi>Greenland,</hi> which arriv'd there in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the Eleventh of <hi>June</hi> following, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with two other Ships, all which were commanded by Captaiu <hi>William Goodler.</hi> The Ship wherein the Captain was ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Bell-ſound;</hi> This of the <hi>Salutation</hi> at the <hi>Foreland:</hi> And the Captain meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:38362:35"/>
with ſtore of Whales, quickly made a Great Voyage, and ſo ſent for the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutation</hi> to take in part of his Train-Oyl: By the way, as they went to him, meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Croſs-Winds, the Maſter ſet-Eight of his Men on Shore to kill ſome Veniſon, in a place where there uſed to be good ſtore. Theſe Men taking with them a Brace of Dogs, a Snaphance, two Lances, and a Tinder-box, went on ſhore, and that day they laid Fourteen Good Deer upon the Ground: And then, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weary, and the Night coming on, they betook themſelves to Reſt, intending the next day to make an end of their Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo to return to their Ship: But the next day proved Foggy, and there was much Ice between the Shore and the Ship, and the Wind coming Southerly, the Ship was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain to ſtand ſo far off into the Sea to be clear of the Ice, that they loſt the ſight of her; and the Weather growing thicker and thicker, they thought fit to Hunt along the Shoar to <hi>Green-Harbour,</hi> and there to ſtay aboard the Ship, till their own Ship ſhould come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Port.</p>
               <p>In this paſſage they killed Eight Deer more, and ſo having laden their Shallop with Veniſon, they kept on their courſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:38362:36"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:38362:36"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:38362:37"/>
to <hi>Green Harbour:</hi> But when they came thither, they found, to their Great Aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, that the Ship was departed. Being thus fruſtrated of their Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and having but three days to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt expiration of their limitted time for their departure out of that Country, they thought it their beſt courſe to make all ſpeed poſſible to <hi>Bell-Sound,</hi> to their Captain; and leſt delay ſhould prove dangerous, they lightned their Shallop by heaving their Veniſon over-board into the Sea, and ſo they haſted all they might, and that night got half-way: But the dark Fog increaſing, they were forced to cove in a point of Land till the next day at Noon: At which time the Weather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing clearer, they haſted forward; but having no Compaſs to direct their courſe by, they wandred up and down ſo long, till the Ships were departed. This filled them with fear and aſtoniſhment, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that neither Chriſtian nor Heathen had ever Inhabited thoſe deſolate Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates: Yea, they had heard that the Merchants had endeavour'd, with proffers of Great Rewards, and of ſufficient Furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and Proviſion of all things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to hire ſome to undertake to Winter in thoſe parts, but could never meet with
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:38362:37"/>
any that would adventure their lives in ſo hazardous an undertaking: They had heard alſo, that the Company of <hi>Moſcovy</hi> Merchants had once procur'd the <hi>Reprieve</hi> of ſome Malefactors condemned to death here in <hi>England,</hi> unto whom they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Pardon, together with Rewards and Proviſion of Cloaths, Victuals, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Neceſſaries, if they would ſtay one Winter there: But when they came thither and took a view of the deſolateneſs of the place, they conceiv'd ſuch horrour and fear in their hearts, that they choſe rather to return for <hi>England,</hi> and there to ſatisfie the Law with the loſs of their lives, than to ſtay in ſo deſolate and darkſom a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. They remembred alſo a more terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Example, of Nine Good and Able Men left there formerly by the ſame Maſter that had now left them, who all died mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably upon the place; and whoſe bodies were fearfully disfigured by the Savage Bears, and Hungry Foxes, which are the only Inhabitants of that comfortleſs Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: All which made them, like amazed Men, to ſtand one looking upon another, every one fore-ſeeing the future Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties both of himſelf and of his Fellows: and that which much encreaſed their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, was, their want of all neceſſary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:38362:38"/>
for the life of Man, having neither Cloaths to keep them warm, and for ſhift, or food to prevent the Miſeries of cruel Famine, nor a houſe wherein to ſhroud themſelves from the extremity of Cold.</p>
               <p>But after a ſpace, knowing that delay in extremities is the Mother of all danger, they began to conceive hope out of the depth of deſpair; and therefore they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted together of the likelieſt courſe for their preſervation in that place, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved upon the opportunity of the next fair weather to go to <hi>Green-Harbour</hi> to kill ſome Veniſon for part of their winter Proviſion, which accordingly ther did, but found not ſo many Deer as they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; yet the firſt day they killed Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and Four Bears to boot, which they alſo intended to eat: The next day they killed Six Deer more, and as they return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they killed Six more, and then the weather proving foul and cold, they laded their Shallop with the Dear and Bears; and finding another Shallop left there as uſually they do from year to year, they laded it with Graves of Whales that had been boiled there that year; and ſo divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelves into thoſe two Shallops, they took the firſt opportunity of return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Bell-Sound</hi> to their Tent, where they
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:38362:38"/>
intended to take up their reſt for the Winter.</p>
               <p>But in their paſſage, the night coming on, and the wind blowing hard, they were forc'd to ſtay in the midſt way at <hi>Bottel Cove</hi> for that night: There they faſten'd their Shallops one to another, and caſting out their Anchor, they left them riding in the <hi>Cove.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here again, for the tryal of their patience, and to teach them to relie more upon God's Providence, than upon any outward means of their own, this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance befel them: The wind blowing hard into the Cove, and their Anchor coming home, their Shallop ſunk into the Sea, and ſo wet all their Proviſion, and ſome of it they found ſwimming up and down by the ſhoar: The ſight thereof, wonderfully troubled them, to ſee the beſt part of their Proviſion, the only hope of their lives under God, in danger either utterly to be loſt, or to be ſpoil'd by the Sea-water, for which they had taken ſuch pains, and run ſo many adventures in the getting of it: and in this their miſery, they ſaw but one remedy, and that was a deſperate one, <hi>viz.</hi> to run into the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrote Sea to their Shallops to ſave the remainder of their Proviſions, now ready
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:38362:39"/>
to be waſhed away by the billows: This they did, and by main force drew the Shallops to the ſhore; then they went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long by the Sea-ſide to gather up ſuch of their Proviſions as was ſwimming up and down: and when the weather prov'd fair, they went on to <hi>Bell-ſound:</hi> where being arrived, they took out their provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and viewed the great Tent which was built of Timber and Boards, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Tiles: The uſe of it was for the Coopers to work and lodge in whilſt they made Cask for the putting up of the Traine-Oyle; and they reſolved to build another ſmaller Tent within that for their Habitations; and accordingly, taking down a leſſer Tent that ſtood near to it, wherein the Landmen lay whilſt they made their Oyle, they fetched their materials from thence, both Boards, Poſts, and Rafters, and from the Chimnies of the Furnaces, they took a thouſand Bricks; they found alſo four Hogſheads of Lime, which mingled with ſand from the ſhoar, made good morter: But the weather was grown ſo extream cold, that they were fain to make two fires on both ſides, to keep their morter from freezing; then they raiſed a wall of one Brick thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt the inner planks of the ſide of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:38362:39"/>
the Tent; but by that time they had wall'd two ſides of their houſe, their Bricks fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo that they were forc'd to build the other two ſides of boards; which being nail'd on both ſides the poſts, they were hollow between, which they fill'd up with ſand, that made it ſo tite, that the leaſt breath of air could not poſſibly annoy them. The length of their Tent was twenty foot, and the breadth ſixteen; their Chimney was the breadth of a deal board, and four foot high; they ciel'd it with boards five or ſix times double, that no wind could poſſibly get through: The door they made as cloſe as they could, and lin'd it with a bed that they found there, which came over both the opening and ſhutting of it: they made no Windows, having no light but what came through the Chimney: then ſet they up four Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins, quartering themſelves two and two in a Cabin; their Beds were the Deer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skins dry'd, which was a warm and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable lodging for them in their diſtreſs: their next care was for firing, and finding ſeven old Shallops which were unſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, they brake them up, and ſtow'd them over the beams in the great Tent to make it the warmer, and to keep the Snow from driving through the Tiles into
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:38362:40"/>
the Tent: and by this time the cold en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, and ſcarce having any day at all, they ſtav'd ſome empty Cask, and brake two old coolers (wherein they coole their Oile) providing whatſoever firing they could without prejudice to the next years Voyage: yet conſidering the ſmall quantity of fuel, the extremity of cold, and the long time of their aboad, they husbanded it as thriftily as poſſibly they could.</p>
               <p>Having thus fitted every thing in the beſt manner they could, on the twelfth of <hi>September,</hi> looking out into the Sound, they eſpied two Sea-horſes lying aſleep on a piece of Ice, whereupon, taking up an old harping-iron, they haſtn'd to them, and firſt ſlew the old one, and then the young; and ſo bringing them aſhore, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them, roaſted, and eat them. Not long after they kill'd another; but the nights and cold weather encreaſing on them, and they viewing their Proviſion, found it too ſmall by half; whereupon they ſtinted themſelves to one reaſonable meal a day, and agreed to faſt <hi>Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days</hi> and <hi>Fridays,</hi> excepting from the Graves or Fritters of the Whale (which was a very loathſome meat) of which they allow'd themſelves ſufficient for
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:38362:40"/>
their preſent hunger: at which diet they continu'd about three months.</p>
               <p>Having finiſhed whatever they could invent for their preſervation; they found that all their Cloaths and Shooes were worn, and torn; to repair which, they had this new deviſe; of Rope-yarn they made thread, and of Whale-bones nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles to ſew their Cloaths withal: But <hi>October</hi> the tenth, the nights being grown very long, and the cold ſo violent, that all the Sea was frozen over; and they having now nothing to exerciſe their minds upon, were troubled with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand imaginations: Sometimes they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail'd their abſence from their Wives and Children, thinking what grief it would be to them to hear of their miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: then thought they of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and what a cutting corraſive it would be to them to hear of their untimely deaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and being thus tormented in their minds with fear, and grief, and pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their bodies with hunger, and cold, the hideous monſter of deſperation pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented his uglieſt ſhape unto them: But thinking it not beſt to give way to grief and fear, they doubled their prayers to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God for ſtrength and patience in their miſeries, by whoſe aſſiſtance, they
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:38362:41"/>
ſhook off their former thoughts, and cheared up themſelves to uſe the beſt means for their preſervation.</p>
               <p>Then for the preſervation of their Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſon, and lengthening of their firing, they thought beſt to roaſt every day half a Deer, and to ſtow it in Hogſheads, which accordingly they did, leaving ſo much raw as would ſerve to roaſt every Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day a quarter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And when this was over, they began again to think of their enſuing miſery, that in caſe God ſhould give them life, yet they were to live as Baniſhed men from all Company; and as if their ſorrows had been too little, they preſently found an encreaſe of it; for their Whale-Fritters, after they had been drenched in the Sea-water, lying cloſe together, were grown mouldy, and ſpoyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and again ſurveying their Bear, and Veniſon, they found that it would not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford them five meals a week, whereupon they were fain to cut off one meal more; ſo that for three months after, four day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the week they fed upon the unſavory mouldy Whale-Fritters, and the other three they feaſted with Bear and Veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: But beſides the want of meat, they now began to want light, ſo that all thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Meals were Suppers: For, from the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:38362:41"/>
of <hi>October,</hi> to the third of <hi>February,</hi> they never ſaw the Sun ſo much as peep above the Horizon: But the Moon, when not obſcured with Clouds, they always ſaw ſhining as bright as in <hi>England:</hi> All which darkſome time, they could not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly tell when it ſhould be day, and when night.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of this darkneſs, they ſought ſome means to preſerve light, and finding a piece of ſheet-lead, and ſome Oyl in the Coopers Tent, and Rope-yarn, they made a Lamp, which they kept con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually burning, which was a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to them in their extremity; yet their wants and miſeries were ſo many, and great, that ſometimes they brake forth into impatient ſpeeches againſt the cauſers of them, but then their Conſciences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain minded them of their own evil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, and ſo they took it as a juſt hand of God for their former wicked lives, or that God intended to make them exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of his Mercy in their wonderful deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance: Humbling themſelves therefore under the mighty hand of God, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated themſelves in prayer two or three times a day, which courſe they conſtantly held all the time of their miſery.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:38362:42"/>
In the beginning of <hi>January,</hi> as the days began to lengthen, the cold began to ſtrengthen; which proceeded to that extremity, that it raiſed bliſters on their fleſh as if they had been burnt with fire, and if at any time they touched Iron, it would ſtick to their fingers like bird<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime: If they went out a doors to fetch in a little water, it would ſo pinch them, that they were ſore as if they had been beaten. In the beginning of Winter, with Pick-axes breaking the Ice daily, they got ſome water on the Sea-ſhore: but after the tenth of <hi>January,</hi> they had none but Snow water which they mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with hot Irons, which was their on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Drink till the twentieth of <hi>May</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
               <p>By the laſt of <hi>January</hi> the days were ſeven or eight hours long, and then view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their victuals again, they found that it would not laſt above ſix weeks longer, which made them fear further Famine; but they had recourſe to God, who they knew, could ſupply them beyond their hopes.</p>
               <p>Looking out on a bright day, they ſaw a great ſhe Bear with her Cub coming towards their Tent, whereupon arming themſelves with their Lances, they went
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:38362:42"/>
forth, and ſtay'd her coming; ſhe ſoon caſt her greedy Eyes upon them, and hoping to devour them, haſted towards them: But with their Lances they gave her ſuch an hearty welcome, that ſhe tumbled upon the ground, biting the Snow for anger: the Cub ſeeing this, eſcap'd by flight: The weather was ſo extream cold, that they were fain preſently to retire into the Tent, and having warmed themſelves, they drew in the dead Bear, wherewith they dined merrily; and this Bear ſerved them twenty days: Only this miſchance they had, eating her Liver, it made their skins peel off; when ſhe was ſpent, they yet fear'd that their Veniſon would not hold out till the Fleet came out of <hi>England;</hi> but God ſent many Bears to their Tent, by times, at leaſt forty, whereof they kill'd ſeven; One of which was exceeding great, at leaſt ſix foot high; ſo that their Food encreaſing, they kept not themſelves to ſuch ſhort com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, but oft eat two or three meals a Day, which much encreaſed their ſtrength.</p>
               <p>By this, the chearful days lengthen'd ſo faſt, that ſeveral ſorts of Fowl reſorted thither. <hi>March</hi> 16th one of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiffs
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:38362:43"/>
went abroad which they never ſaw after; upon the coming of the Fowls, the Foxes, which all winter had kept their Burroughs under the Rocks, came abroad to ſeek for their livings; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they ſet up Traps, which they bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the skin of theſe Fowls, by which means they caught at times fifty Foxes; all which they roſted, and found to be good meat: then taking the Bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skins, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aying the fleſhy ſide upwards, and making ſprings of Whale-bone, they caught about ſixty Fowls as big as Pigeons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>May</hi> the firſt, the weather began to be pretty warm, ſo that they went dayly abroad to ſeek for Proviſion: but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing they could find for many days, till at length they met with abundance of <hi>Willocks</hi> eggs; of which they carried home thirty, intending the next day to fetch a thouſand more, but the day prov'd ſo cold that they could not ſtir out of their Tent. The ſame day there came two ſhips of <hi>Hull</hi> into the Sound, who knowing that ſome men had been left there the year before, being very deſirous to know whether they were dead or alive, the Maſter mann'd forth a ſhallop to go as near the ſhore as they
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:38362:43"/>
could, and ſo over the Ice to the Tent: When theſe men came near the Tent, they haled them with the uſual word of the Sea, crying <hi>Hey:</hi> to which one of them in the Tent anſwered again <hi>Hoe;</hi> which ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den anſwer almoſt amaz'd them all: but perceiving them to be the very men left there, with joyful hearts they embrac'd one another, and ſo coming into the Tent, they ſhew'd the <hi>Hull-Men</hi> the curteſie of the Houſe, giving them ſome Veniſon which was roaſted four months before, and a cup of cold Water, which for novelty ſake, they kindly accepted of them.</p>
               <p>After a little diſcourſe, theſe eight men reſolved to leave their Tent, and to go with them to their ſhip, where they were welcom'd after the heartieſt and kindeſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> manner: and ſo they ſtaid with them till the <hi>London</hi> Fleet came, which was three days after: At which time they went aboard the Admiral, in which Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>William Goodler</hi> was, who made them very welcome, and gave order that they ſhould have any thing that was in the ſhip that might do them good: he gave them Apparel alſo, to the value of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pounds. So that after fourteen days refreſhment, they grew all perfectly
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:38362:44"/>
well: But when ſome of them went to their own Maſter that had left them there, he fell foul upon them, calling them <hi>Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aways,</hi> with other harſh terms far enough from the Civility of an honeſt man. Thus they continu'd in the Fleet until the twentieth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> at which time, with joyful hearts, they ſet ſayl through the foaming Ocean; and though ſometimes croſſed with contrary winds, yet at laſt they came ſafely to an Anchor in the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of <hi>Thames:</hi> and the <hi>Muſcovie</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants dealt very well by them.</p>
               <p>The names of theſe men, were <hi>William Fakely</hi> Gunner: <hi>Edward Pelham</hi> Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Mate, that wrote this ſtory. <hi>John Wiſe,</hi> and <hi>Robert Good-fellow,</hi> Sea-men <hi>Thomas Ayers,</hi> Whale-cutter: <hi>Henry Bet,</hi> Cooper: <hi>John Dawns,</hi> and <hi>Richard Kellet,</hi> Land-men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Greenland,</hi> is a Country that lies very far North-ward in ſeventy-ſeven De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and forty minutes, It's wonderful Mountainous, which Mountains are all the year long covered with Ice and Snow<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The plains in part are bare in Summer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But there grows neither Tree nor He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in it, except Scurvey-graſs and Sorrel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> The Sea is as barren as the Land, affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:38362:44"/>
no Fiſh but Whales, Sea-horſes, Seals, and ſome few ſmall Fiſhes.</p>
               <p>26. In <hi>June</hi> 1668. the <hi>Peach-tree</hi> of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> a ſmall Veſſel of the Burthen of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſixty Tuns, <hi>Edward Dixon</hi> Maſter, came into the <hi>Downs,</hi> bound for <hi>Guinny,</hi> intending there to take in <hi>Negroes,</hi> and to tranſport them to the <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and from thence to come for <hi>London,</hi> where <hi>John Watts,</hi> the Son of <hi>John Watts,</hi> of <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham,</hi> in the Country of <hi>Kent,</hi> Chyrurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhipt himſelf with the conſent of <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Watts,</hi> publick Notary of <hi>Deal;</hi> little dreading that his Nephew, being not above eighteen years old, ſhould meet with ſuch a calamitous Accident. The ſhip had not been long in the <hi>Downs,</hi> but a fair gale preſenting, they ſuddenly hoiſted Sail, God's Providence ſeeming to fill their Sails with proſperous ſucceſs; the firſt place they touched at, was the Gold Coaſt, where they ſtaid not long, but ſail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to old <hi>Calabar,</hi> in the Bith of <hi>Guinny.</hi> They entered a River, called the <hi>Croſs</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver into <hi>Piratts</hi> Iſland. After they had taken in their <hi>Negroes,</hi> and ready to ſail, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Anchor being a peek, the Maſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> up the Boatſwain and three men more, whereof the relater was one, and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:38362:45"/>
commands them to look out the Copper Barrs that were left, and carry them on ſhore to try if they could ſell them: the Boatſwain, with his ſmall Company de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired that they might have Arms with them, not believing the report of ſome that inform'd them they were a harmleſs, and innocent people: they took with them three Muſquets and a Piſtol, and ſo row'd towards the ſhore, but not far from it, unhappily our Match fell into the water, and the ſhip being faln down from that narrow part of the River, nearer the Sea, quite out of our ſight, we were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting what ſhould be ſafeſt for us to do<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we were not willing to precipitate our own Ruine, and were alſo aſhamed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to our ſhip before we had diſpatched what we were commanded to: at length the Boatſwain commanded the Relator <hi>John Watts</hi> on ſhore, to the firſt houſe to light our Match, which we recover'd out of the water, after it was extinct, which he readily obeyed: but before he was twenty Rods from the water-ſide, he was ſeiz'd on by two blacks (or rather Tawny moors) and by them haled above half <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mile up into the Country, and throw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with great violence upon his belly, and ſo compell'd to lye till they ſtript him; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:38362:45"/>
more Company coming to them, they were ſo eager for his poor Canvas appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, that ſome they tore off, others they cut off, and with that ſeveral pieces of his fleſh, to his intolerable pain: with theſe rags, they made little Childrens Aprons to cover their Privities; Linnen and Woolen being ſcarce there. The Boat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwain ſeeing this <hi>John Watts</hi> was thus carried away, was reſolv'd with his other two Companions to have him again, or elſe to venture all their lives for him: They arm themſelves; but whilſt they were conſulting what to do, whether to venture on ſhore, or not, of a ſudden they were beſet with about a dozen men in ſeveral Canoes, but they valiantly maintained their Boat about the ſpace of three hours, for after two of their three Muſquets were diſcharged, they defended themſelves with their Oars, and Boat-hooks. The Boatſwain receiv'd a mortal wound in his Groin, and fell down in the Boat; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two adventur'd in the River, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring by ſwimming to eſcape the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſs hands of cruel Infidels; but the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groes</hi> with their ſwift Canoes ſoon over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took them, and brought them on ſhore to the place where the relator was. The <hi>Negroes</hi> took out the Boatſwain out of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:38362:46"/>
the ſhips boat; and inſtead of endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at all to preſerve life which remained in him, immediately they rob'd him of it; one of them with a keen weapon cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off his head before his Companions faces; and then they prepare for their rare banquet, while he was yet reeking in his blood: they in a barbarous manner cutting off pieces of fleſh from off his But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocks, and his Thighs, and his Arms, and Shoulders, and broiled them on the coals, and with a great deal of impatience, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly eat it before our faces, to our great aſtoniſhment. About fourteen days af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, one of the Company fell ſick, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of being Phyſicians to cure him, they were his Butchers to murther him. They ſerved him as they did the Boatſwain, cut off his head, and broil'd and eat up his fleſh, and rejoyced exceedingly at this rich Banquet. About ten days after, the third fell ſick, whom they ſerved in the ſame manner.</p>
               <p>This was no ſmall cauſe of ſorrow to the Relator; the thoughts of their Inhumane and Barbarous actions ſometimes ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded him with fears and ſorrows, hourly expecting to taſt of the ſaid Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty. Death did not ſeem ſo terrible to him, as the violent manner of it; being
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:38362:46"/>
left now alone, in a ſtrange Country, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of friends or acquaintance, or any thing that might keep up his Spirits: dye he would fain, but not by the hands of Infidels and barbarous Monſters. But the great God that is moſt compaſſionate in the greateſt extremities had pity on him, and notwithſtanding the alteration of the Climate, and the want of Cloaths, and the ſtrangeneſs of his food, which was only herbs, he continued in good health, and had time enough to lament this dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful providence. The Natives who were daily expecting another banquet, met with a diſappointment: either their cuſtoms, or the over-ruling power of God, would not ſuffer them to deſtroy him, he continuing ſtill in health. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they reſolve to ſell him: his <hi>Arannia,</hi> or Maſter, was pretty free to diſcourſe him, which the Relater was capable of, being about three years before in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> where he had learned the <hi>Tata</hi> language, which is eaſily attain'd, being comprehended in a very few words, and all the <hi>Negroes</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>peak it. He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to diſcourſe his Maſter, to know the reaſon of their Cruelty, who told him that he ſhould reſt himſelf contented, who if he were not ſick, ſhould not have
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:38362:47"/>
his head cut off. In the Boat, which in the beginning they took with them, was a Muſquet ſaved of the three which was not diſcharged; which his Maſter, ſome time after he had been with him, brought to him to know the uſe of it: he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd as much as he could to make him apprehend the uſe of it, but ſtill they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt their ignorance: but they command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and threatned him to ſhew the uſe of it. The fear of his maſters diſpleaſure and their inhumanity, cauſed him to ſhoot it off; but the <hi>Negroes,</hi> which expected ſome delightful thing, were fruſtrated, and at the ſuddain noiſe and flaſh of fire (which they very much dread) ran from him, and were greatly affrighted; but quickly after, hearing no more of that noiſe, they came up to him again, and commanded him to do the like: he told them he had not powder, which was the cauſe of the noiſe; but this would not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie theſe Barbarians. He not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to anſwer their expectation, they concluded he was not willing, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to threaten him, and were about to murder him, had not his maſter reſcued him. Upon diſcourſe after with this <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannia,</hi> or Maſter, he began to underſtand the reaſon of their barbarous dealing
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:38362:47"/>
with him and his Friends, he telling him that naturally the People were civil and ſimply honeſt, but if provoked full of revenge; and that this Cruelty was oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd by ſome unhandſome action of carrying a Native away without their leave, about a year before; they reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, if any came aſhore, they ſhould never go off alive. He had not been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſeven weeks in the Country, but his Maſter preſented him to his King, whoſe name was <hi>E-fa-me,</hi> King of the <hi>Blacka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mores,</hi> who immediately gave him to his Daughter, whoſe name was <hi>Oni-jah,</hi> and when the King went abroad, he attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him alſo as his Page, throughout the whole Circuit of his Dominions, which was not above twelve miles, yet boaſting extremely of his power and ſtrength, but glorying exceedingly that he had a White to attend him, whom he employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to carry his Bow and Arrows; at ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral places remote from the Sea-ſide, the people would run away from him for fear, others would fall down and ſeem to worſhip him, and uſe thoſe actions as they do to their God. Their progreſs was never ſo long, but they could return home at night, but never without a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome load of a cup of the Creature. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:38362:48"/>
all the time of the Relators ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude there he never knew him go abroad and come home ſober. They drink of the beſt Palm Wine, and another ſort of ſtrong liquor, call'd <hi>Penrore.</hi> The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator quickly knew how to humour this profound Prince, and if any of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives abuſed him, upon his complaint he had redreſs, as once by ſtriving with a <hi>Negroe,</hi> his arm was broke, which by providence, more than skill, was ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. After ſome months, the King of <hi>Ca-la-nanch,</hi> whoſe name was <hi>E-fn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha,</hi> hearing of this beautiful white, courted his Neighbour Prince, that he would ſell him to him; at length they ſtruck a bargain, and the Relator was ſold for a Cow and a Goat; this King was a very ſober and moderate perſon, free from treacheries and miſchiefs, that the other was ſubject unto; and he would often diſcourſe the Relator, and ask him of his King and Country, and if his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Dominions were as big as his, which were not above twenty-five miles in length, and fifteen in breadth. He told him as much as his underſtanding and years made him capable of, keeping ſtill in the bounds of modeſty, and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating as much as poſſible to the honour,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:38362:48"/>
and dignity of his Soveraign; firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming him of the greatneſs of one of his Kingdoms, the ſeveral Shires and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties it contained, with number of its Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Towns and Caſtles, and the ſtrength of each, the infinite Inhabitants, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of his Subjects. One of theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms was enough to amaze ſufficiently this petty Governour, that he need not to mention any more of his Majeſties Glory and Dignity. It put him into ſuch a profound conſternation, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to find out ſome way to tender his reſpects to this mighty Prince, and no way could he find ſo convenient, as to tell the Relator, that if he could find but a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, he would let him go to <hi>England,</hi> to tell his Majeſty of the great favour and reſpect he had for him. This did not a little rejoyce our Engliſh-man. Withall the King told him, that he would ſend him a Preſent, which ſhould be two Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bareets or Goats, which they do value at a very high rate; the King having not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 16 or 18. He tells the King, that the King of <hi>England</hi> had many thouſands of his Subjects that were under the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Gentlemen, which had a thouſand of Sheep a piece; the fleſh of which, they valu'd at a very much higher rate than
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:38362:49"/>
Goats. Though our Engliſh-man lived very handſomely with this <hi>E-fn-man-cha,</hi> King of the <hi>Ca-la-nanch,</hi> yet his deſires and his hopes were ſtill for his Native Country: at length he obtain'd a promiſe from his King, that the firſt Engliſh ſhip that came into that Road, ſhould have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to Releaſe or Purchaſe him; this very much rejoyced his heart: now he thought every day a year, till he could hear of, or ſee ſome Engliſh ſhip arrived. Many times when he was alone, his heart would be oppreſt with ſighs and ſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bings, when ke thought of his Relations, and the comfortable ſociety that they had together; that it ſhould be his ſad lot to be captivated amongſt barbarous Infidels. Oftentimes did he walk down to the Sea-ſide, ſometimes with hopes, ſometimes with fear, earneſtly expecting the wind of Gods providence to blow in ſome Engliſh Ship thither: his often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the Sea-ſide was diſcerned by one <hi>Ja-ga,</hi> a Wizard, and the chiefeſt in three or four Kingdoms there-abouts; they are perſons that the Natives give very much credit to, and on any difficult occaſion, run to them for ſatisfaction. The famous Delphean Oracle was never had in greater adoration, than the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:38362:49"/>
Speeches of theſe Moriſh Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards. Though they have infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of them in every place, yet this <hi>Ja-ga</hi> had the moſt renown amongſt them; and one day he comes to him, and very kindly ask'd him, Why he ſo very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten frequented that place? he told him, To ſee if he could diſcover any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Veſſel to come in there: but he being not acquainted with his Great fame, Askt him When he did believe there would one come in? not that he was willing to give credit to any of their Divinations, but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing that he thereby ſhould pleaſe him and anſwer his expectation. <hi>Ja-ga</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately told him, That the Fifteenth day after an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ship ſhould come into the Road. Then he askt him, Whether that Ship ſhould carry him away. To this he anſwer'd doubtfully, but told him, That he ſhould be offer'd to the Maſter of the ſhip, and if they could not agree, but that he ſhould come to Shore again, he ſhould not be Sold, and that in a very ſhort time after he ſhould dye for Grief. Theſe Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen days ſeem'd very long and tedious; many a look did he caſt on the Sea with an Aking heart: The Fourteenth day he went to the higheſt Hill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but to no purpoſe, for he could diſcover no
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:38362:50"/>
Ship: next Morning he went again two or three times, but ſaw none: about two or three hours after came running into <hi>E-fn-man-cha,</hi> ſome of the Moores, and told him there was a Canoe coming, ſo they called our Ships; at which our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh-man heartily rejoyc'd, hoping then to be releaſt forthwith, yet durſt not ſhew his joy for fear of puniſhment or of death; for though he lived better now than with his firſt Maſter, yet his ſervice was far worſe than the Slaves in <hi>Turkey,</hi> and their Diet worſe than Dogs-meat; therefore had he cauſe enough of inward Joy; the Ship came immediately in, and he highs away preſently to <hi>Ja-ga,</hi> to know if it were an Engliſh Ship, who reſolved him that it was; it happened to be the St. <hi>Maloes</hi> Merchant, Captain <hi>Royden</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, who haſten'd to diſpatch his Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, took in his Negroes, and was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſail, and our Engliſh-man heard ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a word what ſhould become of him, the King never offering to ſell him; this put him on a reſolution to endeavour to make an eſcape, and to that end had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared a piece of Timber which he had drawn near the water-ſide, on which he intended to paddle to the Ship, which then lay about a League from the Shore. Juſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:38362:50"/>
by the Sea-ſide; as he was about to launch his little floating Stick, he eſpied a Great <hi>Aligator,</hi> which will devour a Man at a Mouthful; this made him alter his Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and reſolve rather to live with Inhumane Infidels, than to throw himſelf into ſo imminent a danger, which would have been little leſs than ſelf-murther. But the next day, which I may call a day of <hi>Jubilee,</hi> Almighty God opened the heart of the King to let the poor Engliſh Man go: he ſent him in a Canoe, placed between a Negroe's Legs, with ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to Guide this ſmall Veſſel, for fear he ſhould leap over board and ſwim to the Ship. At a diſtance from the Ship he hail'd her in the Engliſh Tongue, which was no ſmall cauſe of admi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation to thoſe on Board to hear an Engliſh Tongue out of their Canoes: The Negroes gave him leave to ſtand up and ſhew himſelf to the Captain, to whom he gave an Account how four were left there, and only he preſerv'd. It was a pretty while before they could ſtrike a B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rgain, though the Captain was reſolv'd not to leave him behind. Several times the Negroes pad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led away with their Canoe, reſolving not to part with him; but what with his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties and promiſes, he perſwaded them
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:38362:51"/>
to the Ship again, and they deliver'd him on board for Forty five Copper Bars and Iron Bars; each Copper bar being about the bigneſs of a Youths little finger, the Iron bars a little bigger. Now were his joys compleated, he thought himſelf, as it were, caught up into the Third Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens; he could hardly perſwade himſelf but it was a Dream or Viſion, and that he did not really ſee Engliſh faces, or em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Engliſh bodies. It was ſome time before he could throw himſelf at the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains feet, and acknwledge his infinite cauſe of joy in himſelf, and thankfulneſs to him for his deliverance from ſuch a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Captivity; that he that lately was a ſlave to Infidels, that worſhip they know not what, ſhould now ſee the Faces of Chriſtians, and joyn with them in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiping the true God; and to him firſt he offer'd up the Sacrifice of hearty thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, that had ſent his Angel to redeem him from ſo cruel a bondage. When he came on board, his hair was very long, and his skin tawny <hi>(Malatto-</hi>like) having gone naked all the time he was there, and frequently anointing himſelf with Palm-Oyl he looked like a Tawny Moore; but immediately the Seamen aboard with Chriſtian-like hearts, apparelled him. The
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:38362:51"/>
Maſter commanded to hoiſt ſail, and having a fair wind, they ſailed to <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does,</hi> where Captain <hi>Royden</hi> was to tarry ſome time; but the Relator earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to go to his Native Country, and his Relations, got paſſage to the <hi>Downs,</hi> in the <hi>Katherine</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Captain <hi>South</hi> Commander, which through Gods goodneſs in a few weeks arrived in the <hi>Downs,</hi> where the Relator was put on ſhore to his Unkle Mr. <hi>Richard Watts</hi> of <hi>Deal,</hi> his great joy and ſatisfaction, who took this relation from his own mouth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Relation of Dr.</hi> William Johnſon, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a moſt Remarkable Sea-Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; in his own words.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>27. We went aboard from <hi>Harwich,</hi> on Michaelmas day, <hi>Sept.</hi> 29. 1648. in the <hi>William</hi> and <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Ipſwich, Daniel Morgan,</hi> Maſter, and having a fair wind, we ſet Sail; I being Sea-ſick, went to bed, but about four a Clock in the Afternoon, the Maſter of the Ship came into our Cabin with more haſt than he was wont, which made me ask him whither all was well, who like a tender-hearted man, who is loth to tell his dying Friend, that he is ſo nigh his end, replyed all is well, yet when I ſaw him ſhift himſelf with ſuch
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:38362:52"/>
haſt, I roſe from my Bed, and crawled upon the Deck, where I ſaw a ſad ſpectacle, the Ship having ſprung a leak, or rather a plank, was ready to ſink, upon which, every man was affrighted, one was at his Prayers, another wringing his Hands, a third his eyes ſhedding of tears, when he had no need of more ſalt water; but after this, they fell to work, but were buſie in doing nothing: The Maſters Mate, who went to ſearch the Leak, told us with a ſad countenance, trembling hands, gnaſhing of Teeth, a quivering Tongue, and words half ſpoken, <q>That the Leak could not be ſtopt, and the water came in ſo faſt upon us, that we muſt periſh in this moment.</q> Upon which we preſently caſt out our Long-boat, and ſhot off eight or nine Guns to another Ship, who came out with us, to come to our relief, then with ſome diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty we all got into the Boat, and God be thanked, came clear of the Ship, whoſe ſails now lay flat upon the Water, and now we were rowing we know not whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for the other Ship came not to our relief, which made us have hard thoughts of them without cauſe, for we underſtood that both the Ship, and all the men periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſame hour. Now were we
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:38362:52"/>
without all hope, for it blew half a ſtorm, and we were in a ſmall Veſſel, many Leagues from the Shore, without Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, or proviſion to ſuſtain us, being ſtarved likewiſe with Cold, as well as for want of Victuals, having nothing in our Boat, but a ſmall Kettle which ſerved to caſt out the water, and three bags of pieces of eight of three hundred pound Sterling, which would neither feed us, nor keep us warm; in this diſtreſs we went to Prayers, and it pleaſed God to hear us, and ſend a Ship to us, even in the moment of Death, which we endeavoured to come to, and he likewiſe to us, but the ſtorm was ſo great, we could not reach one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though when it was dark, he hung out a light, and we to let him know we were alive, ordered that when a wave took us up, we ſhould give a great ſhout, which we did ſo loud, that I believe our cry was heard to Heaven, for by Gods miraculous aſſiſtance we got near the Ship, and ſoon after, all ſafe into it; the next day it blew fair for <hi>Norway,</hi> whither we were bound, and about twelve at noon we ſaw the Coaſt, which being ragged, and full of Rocks, we reſolved to ſtay till next morning before we went in, and then ſate down to meat, and eat very
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:38362:53"/>
heartily, being kindly entertain'd by the honeſt <hi>Norwegian;</hi> about ten a clock at night, we laid us down to reſt, after having prayed, and ſet our watch, but immediately this our ſecond Ship ran with full Sails upon a Rock, and gave ſo great a Crack, as was able to awake the moſt dead aſleep among us, and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners cryed out, Mercy, Mercy, it pleaſed God, that the Ship ſtruck it ſelf ſo faſt in the cleft of a Rock, with her Bow over the main Rock, that the former part of her ſtood firm, but breaking in the ſtorm, one of the Sea-men leaped from the bow of the Ship, upon the Rock, with a Rope in his hand, which was faſtened to one of our Maſts, and held it with ſo ſtiff a hand, that another ſlipt down by it, and ſo all our Company that eſcaped, being Twenty Eight in number, came ſafe to the Rock; I was the laſt that came down the Ship that way, for in that very moment ſhe gave way, which the Maſter perceiving, who was ſtill aboard, made lamentable moan to us, to help him, which we endeavoured to the utmoſt, but the Ship broke, and ſunk im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately; there was this good man, and four of the Marriners drowned; I ſaw the Maſter, with a light in his hand fall
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:38362:53"/>
into the Sea, the ſaddeſt ſight that I ever yet beheld in this world, and that which pierced my very Soul, to ſee him that ſaved our Lives, loſe his own: Now were we in the dark, upon the Rock, but knew not where, our feet being cut upon the ſharp ſtones, at length, we happened of a hole in the Rock, which was a warm ſhelter againſt the wind; and when morning came, where we could ſee no Land, only had a Glimps of the Coaſt of <hi>Norway</hi> at a great diſtance; We grew hungry, but had nothing to fiſh, but our Arms, with which we drew up ſome ſmall Muſcles, and they we eat heartily, but we burnt with thirſt, and I would have given all I had for a draught of freſh water, which would have been more wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come than the Gold of Ophir, though nothing is ſo mean in our eſteem; but we were forced to drink Salt-water, which increaſed our thirſt; we now ſaw a Ship coming towards us with full Sails, and we waved our hats to them, but they went off, and never came near us; we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took our ſelves to our old Remedy, Prayers, the <hi>Danes</hi> firſt ſinging one of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ther</hi>'s Pſalms, fell to their Prayers, and I prayed as long as I was able to ſpeak, and then lay'd my ſelf down on the Rock,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:38362:54"/>
thinking I ſhould riſe no more in this World: But I overheard one of the Sea-men ſay, <q>Let us make a Raft, and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to Sea, I had rather be drowned than lye here and be ſtarved;</q> They all concluded of it, though dangerous, and the Sea having fallen from the Rock, had left our Sails, Maſts, and Anchors, with part of the Ship thereon, wherewith they ſoon made a ſlight Boat, and it being a great calm, the reſt paſt through the beaches with four men in it, and had it touched only on them, they would have rent it in pieces, however through Gods goodneſs, they arrived ſafe in <hi>Norway,</hi> and returned with ſeveral Boats, ſo that we came all of us once more to Land, and were entertained at an honeſt Lutheran Parſons houſe, where after we had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued for ſome days, with little money and much thanks we parted, and came to <hi>Frederick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> where the People run after us in the Street, and with compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Eyes gave us what we wanted, without asking; from thence we went to <hi>Oſterſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and there went aboard an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ship, we had not been above two or three <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at Sea, but there was a ſad deſtraction, the Marriners again cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Mercy, Mercy, for we had almoſt
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:38362:54"/>
fallen foul on a Rock under water, which we did not ſpy till we were upon it, but by the mercy of God, we ſailed cloſe by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, and yet eſcaped it, the leaſt touch of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t had been our ruine; about noon we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame clear of all the Rocks on the Coaſt of <hi>Norway,</hi> and were ſailing for <hi>England,</hi> with a fair Gale of Wind, but in this proſperity, another ſad accident befel us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his third Ship ſprang a leak, and began <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſwim within, as well as without, and we had no way to relieve our ſelves, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y pumping (for the Leak could not be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound) which we did day and night, or four or five days together, when it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leaſed God, we came ſafe, though in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reat deal of danger, becauſe of our otten Ship; into <hi>Yarmouth</hi> Road, for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ind being very high, had like to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riven us upon a <hi>Scotch</hi> Veſſel, who cryed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut as well as we, but we happily miſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m, and ſo ſafely arrived in <hi>Yarmouth</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>own, through the wonderful mercy of God. <hi>Deus Nobiſcum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The great Dangers, and Merciful Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of</hi> William Okely <hi>and his Company from Slavery in a Canvas Boat,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>In the Year 1639. We took Ship at <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aveſend,</hi> in the <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Mr.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:38362:55"/>
                  <hi>Boarder</hi> Maſter, bound for the Iſle of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> five weeks we lay in the <hi>Downs,</hi> waiting for a wind, and then we ſet Sail, and came to an Anchor near the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> but by this time all the Beer in our Ship ſtunk, and we were forced to throw it overboard, and ſo take in Vinegar to mix with Water for our Voyage; the next Lords day we ſet Sail again, and coming between the Iſland, and the main Land, we ſtuck faſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the Sands, but the Tide coming in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heaved us off: the ſixth day after ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſetting Sail from the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> we diſcovered three <hi>Turks</hi> men of War, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> chaſed us, and at break of day boarde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and took us; having kept us clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Priſoners at Sea, at the end of five or ſix weeks, they brought us to <hi>Algiers,</hi> when I was ſold for a ſlave the firſt Market da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to a Patron, who told me, <q>I muſt allow him two Dollars a Month, and live aſhore where I would, and get it when I could, though I knew not where t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> levy the leaſt Mite of it:</q> Wandring u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and down I met with an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his little Shop, who Traded with <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco,</hi> and a few other things; I beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his Partner with a little Money I h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> reſerved, and a ſmall modicum my Patr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:38362:55"/>
had allowed me for my ſtock; Here I got money and hired a Celler, where I laid up ſome other of my Goods; when weary of my ſlavery, I formed a deſign for my Liberty, and communicated it to <hi>John Anthony</hi> Carpenter, <hi>William Adams</hi> Brick-layer, <hi>John Jephs</hi> Seaman, <hi>John</hi> a Carpenter, and two others, men of able Bodies, and uſeful in the intended project, which was to contrive the Model of a Boat, which being formed in parcels, and afterward put together, might be the means of our eſcape: They approved the Propoſal, and in my Cellar we began our work, we provided firſt a piece of Timber of twelve foot long to make the Keel, but becauſe it was impoſſible to convey it of that length out of the City, but it muſt be ſeen and ſuſpected; we therefore cut it in two pieces and fitted it for jointing juſt at the middle, and then we provided Ribs, after which we made the Boat Water-tight, and becauſe boards would require much hammering, and that noiſe was like to betray us, we bought as much ſtrong Canvas as would cover our Boat twice over upon the Convex of the Carine; we provided alſo as much <hi>Pitch, Tar,</hi> and <hi>Tallow,</hi> as would ſerve to make it a kind of Tarpawling Cerecloth
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:38362:56"/>
to ſwaddle the Naked Body of our Infant Boat; of two Pipe ſtaves ſawed at the Corners, we made two things to ſerve for Oars, and for our Proviſion, we had a little Bread, and two Leather Bottles full of freſh Water, we alſo remembered to buy as much Canvas as would ſerve for a Sail, we carried out theſe in parts and parcels fitted them together in the Valley about half a mile from the Sea, whither Four of our Company carried the Boat on their Shoulders, and the reſt followed them, at the Sea-ſide we ſtript, put our clothes into the Boat, and carried it and them as far into the Sea as we could wade, and then all ſeven got into the Boat, but finding ſhe was over laden, two of the Sea-men were content to ſtay on ſhore; having bid them farewel, we lanched out, <hi>June</hi> 30. 1644. The Bill of Lading was <hi>John Anthony, William Adams, John Jephs, John</hi> the Carpenter, and <hi>William Okely;</hi> Four of us wrought continually at the Oar, the Fifth was to free the Boat of that Water, which by degrees leaked through our Canvas, our Bread was ſoon ſpoiled with the ſoaking in the Salt-water, our Freſh-water ſtunk of the Tanned Skins, and <hi>Owze,</hi> yet we complained not, three days with good
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:38362:56"/>
Husbandry our Bread laſted us, but then Pale Famine ſtar'd us in the Face; Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter indeed we might have, but it muſt be Salt, out of the Sea, or that which had been ſtrain'd through our own Bodies, and that we choſe of the two; but we muſt not have that after a while, unleſs we would accept of the other firſt; and the miſery was, that did not aſſwage our Thirſt, but increaſe it; the Wind too, for ſome time was full againſt us, but God rebuked it, and made it our Friend; a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond inconvenience was, that our Labour was without intermiſſion; and a third, the extremity of the Heat by day, the ſeaſon raging hot, the beginning of <hi>July,</hi> and we wanted freſh-water to cool the Heat, our Labour made it inſupportable to our Bodies, and our little hope made it as grievous to our Souls; one help we had, a poor one, he that emptied the Boat, threw the Water on the Bodies of the other to cool them; but our Bodies thus ſchorched and cooled roſe up in Bli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters all over; great pain we felt, great dangers we were in, great miſeries we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dur'd, great wants we were under, and had nothing but a little hope, food, and ſtrength: If any Ask by what Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we Steered our courſe to <hi>Mayorck,</hi>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:38362:57"/>
whither we deſign'd to go; for the day a Pocket Dial did ſupply the place of a Compaſs, by Night the Stars when they appear'd, and when not, we gueſſed our way by the motion of the Clouds: Four days and nights were we in this woful plight; on the fifth, all hope that we ſhould be ſav'd was periſh'd, ſo that we left off our Labour, becauſe we had no ſtrength left, only we emptied the Boat of Water; but then God ſent us ſome Relief, for as we lay hulling up and down, we diſcover'd a Tortoiſe, not far from us aſleep in the Sea; had <hi>Drake</hi> diſcover'd the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet, he could not have more Rejoyc'd; we took up our Oars, ſilently rowed to our Prey, took it into the Boat with Great Triumph; we cut off her Head, and let her Bleed into a Pot, we drank the Blood, eat the Liver, and ſucked the fleſh: it wonderfully refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Spirits, and we picked up ſome crumbs of hope: about Noon we thought we diſcover'd Land; it's impoſſible to expreſs the joy of our raiſed Souls at this apprehenſion, we Wrought hard, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter further Labour were fully ſatisfy'd that it was Land, and proved to be <hi>May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ork,</hi> which we kept within ſight of all day. <hi>July</hi> the 6th. about Ten at Night we
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:38362:57"/>
came under the Iſland, and crept as near the Shore as we could or durſt, till we found a convenient place, where we might thruſt in our Weather-beaten Boat; when we were come to Land we were not inſenſible of our deliverance; but though we had eſcap'd the Sea, we might die at Land; We had no Food ſince we eat the Liver, and drank the Blood of the Tortoiſe; therefore <hi>John Anthony</hi> and my ſelf were ſent out to Scout abroad for Freſh-Water, becauſe we ſpake ſome Spaniſh; We came to a Watch-Tower of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> ſpake to them on the Watch, told them our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, earneſtly begged ſome Freſh-Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſome Bread; he threw us down an old Mouldy Cake, but ſo long as it was a Cake, Hunger did not conſider its Mouldineſs; then he directed us to Freſh-Water which was hard by; We ſtood not telling of Stories, we remembred our Brethren left with our Boat, and obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Centinels Directions, came to a Well, where there was a Pot with ſtrings to draw with; we drank a little Water, and eat a bit of our Cake, but the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage was ſo diſuſed, that we had much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do to force our Throats to relieve our clamorous Stomachs; we return to our
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:38362:58"/>
Boat, and acquaint them with the Good Succeſſes of our Embaſſy, and all prepare to make to the Well, ſo tying our Boat as faſt as we could to the ſhore, we left her to Mercy: Now we are at the Well which hath Water therein, and we have ſomething to draw, but God muſt give us a Throat to ſwallow; for <hi>William A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> attempting to drink, after many Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſays, was not able to ſwallow it, but ſtill the Water return'd, ſo that he ſunk down to the ground, fainting, ſaying, <hi>I am a dead Man:</hi> but after much ſtriving he took a little; ſo refreſhed with our Cake and Water, we lay by the Well ſide till the Morning; when it was clear day, we again went to the Watchman, intreating him to direct us the ready way to the next Houſe or Town, where we might find re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief; he civilly pointed us to one about Two Miles off, and long it was ere our Bliſtering Feet could overcome the tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of that little way: When we came thither, the honeſt Farmer moved with our Relation, ſent us Bread and Water, and Olives, and ſeeing us Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Beggars, inlarged his Civility to us, called us into his Houſe, and gave us good warm Bean Pottage, which ſeem'd to me the moſt pleaſant Food that ever I eat in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:38362:58"/>
my Life, then we advanced to the City of <hi>Mayorck,</hi> about Ten Miles from that place; that Night we lay by a Well ſide, and in the Morning we entred the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs; the Vice-Roy was informed of us, and we were commanded to appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, who, after he had Examin'd us, and heard our Story, order'd we ſhould be maintain'd at his own Coſt, till we could have Paſſage to our own Countrey, But our Engliſh Ships ſeldom Trading thither, we Petition'd the Vice-Roy for Paſſage in the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Gallies, which were in the Road bound for <hi>Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant,</hi> which he graciouſly granted us; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome other Troubles we met with contrary Winds, and it was five Weeks ere we could reach the <hi>Downs,</hi> where we arriv'd in <hi>Sept.</hi> 1644. The Commander of the Ship was Captain <hi>Smith</hi> of <hi>Rother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hithe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Thomas Saunders,</hi> my Wives Brother, being in <hi>Mayorck</hi> not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we came from thence, ſaw our Boat hung for a Monument upon the ſide of the Great Church there; and Mr. <hi>Robert Hales</hi> was there 1671. and aſſures me, that he ſaw the Naked Ribs and Skele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton of it then hanging in the ſame place. <hi>Wanly</hi>'s Hiſt. <hi>Man,</hi> p. 642.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:38362:59"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Merciful Preſervation and Deliverance of Captain</hi> Bloſe <hi>and his ſhips Company, who were Caſt away in an Iſland of Ice near</hi> Ruſſia, <hi>this preſent year</hi> 1697.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>October</hi> the <hi>7th.</hi> 1696. We came from <hi>Archangel</hi> in <hi>Ruſſia</hi> in the <hi>Riga</hi> Merchant, Burthen 300 Tuns, 18 Guns, <hi>Samuel Bloſe</hi> Commander. The 8th we had the Wind at <hi>North Weſt</hi> by <hi>Weſt,</hi> we plied to Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and it blew very hard; the 10th we took two Reefs in our Topſails; the 12th we took in our Topſails, and Ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed Coſts; the 13th about One in the Morning we Sprung a Leak, in ſo much that we were forced to ſet both our Pumps to Work, and bear away before the Wind; yet ſtill the Water increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and the 14th we cut our Main-Sail from the Yard, and let him fly over-board, the Weather being ſo exceſſive thick by reaſon of the extraordinary much Snow that then fell, that we could not ſee the Land, nor any place where we could run our Ship Aſhore to ſave our Lives; The 15th in the Morning, about One of the Clock, by Fortune, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected of us, before we ſee any Land, we ſtruck upon an Iſland, called by the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:38362:59"/>
                  <hi>Ruſſes, Muſſoves,</hi> lying in the <hi>Miſſen Gulf,</hi> which by the Miraculous hand of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> gotten well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore, for as God of his wonderful goodneſs ſo order'd it, we ſtruck about High Water, and as the Water fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, our Ship dryed, ſo that we got all ſafe to Land without any harm; and if it had pleaſed God we happen'd ever ſo little, either to one ſide or the other, we ſhould have all periſh'd amongſt the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlands of Ice. When we got all aſhore, we made us a Tent, and when it was Day, looking about us, ſaw ſomething like Houſes; ſo our Captain and a Dutch Merchant Paſſenger that we had on Board of our Ship, and our Doctor, went to ſee what they were, thinking to find ſome Inhabitants, but they could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ind none: then we went Aboard our Ship, and got all our Beef aſhore that we could find, about One hundred Weight of Bisket Bread, which was all the Bread we could find; then we Calculated that our Beef at Four Pieces a day, would ſerve us till the middle of <hi>May,</hi> and every Man one Bisket a Day; but that would laſt but a ſmall time: Beſides, we got a ſhore Three Boxes of Candles, which was a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to us in our neceſſity, by reaſon we
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:38362:60"/>
had not above Three hours Day. Then we got all our things we had ſaved to the Houſe that we ſaw; and going about diſcover'd a great many more Houſes, and we went to them to ſee what we could find, expecting to ſee ſome People, but there was none but empty Cask, ſo we came home to the place that we had car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried our things to again; but, as God would have it, juſt againſt the Houſe that we had taken for our Habitation, in the Snow, we ſaw Two Cask, and we went and found them both full of Rye Meal, which was a Joy beyond meaſure to us in our Extremity; and then we found another Cask with a Kneeding-Tub in it: <hi>December</hi> the Firſt, the Dutch Merchant, and Four more of our hands went out and took a Compaſs, and Proviſion with them, upon Diſcovery, hoping to ſee ſome body to ſpeak to, that we might know where we were, but they could find no Inhabitants, the Courſe they ſteered was S. E. but when they came to turn back, their Compaſs unhung, and they not minding it, went up and down a long time, and at length came to the ſame place where they were when they firſt turned back; then they looked more earneſtly upon their Compaſs, and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:38362:60"/>
found it unhung, they hung it, and came the direct way home again; but when they came in ſight of a Houſe that was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Two Miles off of our Houſe, the Merchant and one more Travelling bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the other Three, went before, and promis'd them to make a Fire againſt they came; but the Weather being ſo ſevere, they were not able to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, but were Starved with the Cold before they could get up to us: So the Lord, of his great Mercy, made Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for us until the Firſt of <hi>March,</hi> it being a Sabbath day, and we at our Devotion, one of our Boys being at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe Boiling of our Victuals, ſaw ſome Men upon the Iſland, he fell down, being much ſurpriz'd, but ſoon got up again, and run and told us; upon which we left our Prayers, and run to ſee what they were; our Merchant could ſpeak the Language, which was the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of all our Lives, for otherways they would have Murther'd us for break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down their Houſes, and Eating their Proviſions that we found upon the Iſland, for they would not be perſwaded but we were Pirats and Robbers, by reaſon that we werre Building of a Small Veſſel for our own Security, of carrying us to the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:38362:61"/>
Main when the Ice broke up; but our Merchant ſpeaking their Language, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded them, and promiſed them to make them Satisfaction for what Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage we had done them; for we broke down Two of their Houſes for Firing: So they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rned us out of our Houſes, and took our Meal from us. The Men that came over were in Number 500, Ten Men in a Boat, they came there to kill Seales: They asked us what we had ſeen? We told them, Nothing but Two Ravens. They made very ſtrange of it, and would not believe it: For they told us, That none of them could live there but Six Weeks in the Year, whether they catcht Fiſh or not, the Iſland was ſo Haunted. Soon after the <hi>Ruſſians</hi> came there, that Man that ſaved his Life, and got well home with the Merchant, when the other Three were Starved with the Cold Died, that was Four that was Dead, our Complyment at firſt was 27, but then we had but 23 Living: Then our Merchant went to the <hi>Ruſſians,</hi> and deſired them to put us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver, and he would ſatisfie them for it: They grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed we ſhould have Six Boats, and 60 Men to Drag us over the Ice, for it was Seven Leagues from the Main, and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:38362:61"/>
all full of Iſlands of Ice between, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that they were 24 hours coming over when they came upon the ſaid I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland: But it pleaſed the Lord ſo to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it that after they had dragg'd us o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Two ſmall Iſlands of Ice, that as God parted the Red-Sea for the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to paſs through, ſo he parted the Ice from us, inſomuch that we got over in Six houres times, which the <hi>Ruſsians</hi> told us was never ſo before. But when we came over we lay where there was 1000 Men a Fiſhing, The firſt Night: and the next Morning we hired Sledges to drag us to ſome place Inhabited: The Beaſts that dragg'd the Sledges along they call <hi>Roeys,</hi> they are like Dear, but larger: We were forc'd to be Dragg'd, we could not Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel our Limbs were ſo diſabled with the Cold before we got off the aforeſaid I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland: beſides the Snow was of ſuch a vaſt thickneſs, and ſo hard Frozen, that we could find no Path, if we could Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel never ſo well, If the <hi>Shamakes,</hi> as they call them, had not ſhown us the way; the firſt Night of our Journey up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sledges our Carpenters Mate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo we made a Hole in the Snow and put him in, and left him. Then our
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:38362:62"/>
Captain, and the Merchant, and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, being but ſingle in a Sledge, and we near double, went faſter than us to the next Town to provide Victuals and freſh Sledges for us againſt we came; and when we came to that Town we got Sledges that had Horſes to draw them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, ſo we Rid Night and Day till we came to <hi>Archangel;</hi> the Third day of our Travels another of our Men Died, and the Fifth day another; the former we Buryed in the Ground, becauſe we were nigh a Town, but the other we Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed in the Snow: So that when we came to <hi>Archangel,</hi> out of our 27 Men, we had but 20 left. <hi>March</hi> the <hi>17th</hi> we came off the aforeſaid Iſland, and we Travell'd Night and Day, except the firſt Night, until the <hi>25th</hi> of the ſame Month. Two days after we came to <hi>Archangel</hi> we loſt another Man. At <hi>Archangel</hi> our Captain got Stoves for us to inhabit in, and ſent us Proviſion, where we remain'd till the <hi>6th</hi> day of <hi>June,</hi> when there came in Six Sail of <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> being the Firſt that came that year, who divided us amongſt them, and brought us to <hi>Greenland,</hi> and from thence ſome of us were brought to <hi>Holland,</hi> and ſome to <hi>Hamborough,</hi> from whence Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:38362:62"/>
of us got Paſſage to <hi>England,</hi> where we Arriv'd the Fifteenth of <hi>November,</hi> 1697. Two went to the <hi>Straits,</hi> and our <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchant tarried in <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Account is given by <hi>Francis Lee,</hi> who was Boatſwain of the Ship, and Atteſted by others now Living in <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:38362:63"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Seaman's Preacher;</hi> OR, Sea-Dangers and Deliverances Improv'd; in a SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Acts 27. 18, 19, 20.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>18. And being exceedingly toſſed with a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, the next day they lightned the Ship.</p>
                  <p>19. And the third day, we caſt out with our own hands, the tackling of the Ship.</p>
                  <p>20. And when neither Sun nor Stars appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and no ſmall Tempeſt lay on us, all hope that we ſhould be ſaved, was then taken away.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN this Chapter we have a full Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative of <hi>Paul</hi>'s Voyage to <hi>Rome,</hi> in all the circumſtances of it; it ſeems <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:38362:63"/>
kept a Journal, and ſo Recorded this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable Voyage for the uſe of ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Generations. 1. We have the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of his Voyage, <hi>(viz.) Paul</hi> being then a Sufferer and a Priſoner, he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and ſo is ſent to <hi>Rome,</hi> and there bears a faithful Teſtimony for Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>(verſ.</hi> 1.) 2. We have the Dangers that occurred in the Voyage, and theſe are alſo carefully Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated <hi>(verſ.</hi> 9.) Now much time was ſpent, and Sailing was now dangerous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Faſt was already paſt: This was the yearly Fast of the <hi>Jews,</hi> on which the attonement for all the people was made by the High-Prieſt, in the holy of holies; which day was the 10. of the 7th Month, <hi>(Lev.</hi> 16. 29.) which partly agreed with our <hi>September</hi> and <hi>October,</hi> in which time the Sea, was not Sailed in, by the Ancients, until the beginning of <hi>March,</hi> becauſe of the ſhortneſs of the days, and the violence of the Tempeſts, they were prone to in thoſe Parts, this is the ſenſe of Interpreters upon the place. 1. Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Voyage we read of, is this, the winds were contrary, <hi>(verſ.</hi> 4.) this is ſpoken of the Voyage of the Diſciples, The winds were contrary. 2. Danger, there aroſe not only a contrary wind,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:38362:64"/>
but a violent wind, called an <hi>Euroclydon, (verſ.</hi> 14.) ſome read it a Whirle-wind, but it is ment of an <hi>Eaſt-</hi>wind, which raiſes the Sea mightily. 3. The Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt was ſo great and violent upon them, that they were glad to let the Ship drive, <hi>(verſ.</hi> 15.)</p>
            <p>3. We have not only the Danger in this Voyage, but their marvelous Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance and Preſervation; for they came off all of them with their lives, <hi>(verſ.</hi> 44.) the particulars whereof you may ſee.</p>
            <p>In the Text we have three things ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable. 1. Their endeavors in this great diſtreſs to preſerve themſelves. 1. They lightned the Ship, and what was it ſhe was laden with? it was Wheat, <hi>(verſ.</hi> 38.) They lightned the Ship, and caſt the Wheat into the Sea; thus did <hi>Jonah</hi>'s Mariners caſt out the Wares. Alas, what are theſe things, but lumber to lives? if it were Gold, it muſt go for Life. <hi>Skin for skin and all that a man hath will he give for his life.</hi> Then what ſhould a man give for his Soul? what will a man give for his Soul? what will a man give in exchange for his Soul? 2. Endeavor; they caſt out the Tack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of their Ship; any thing they part with to ſave their lives, though never ſo uſeful to them; even that which was
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:38362:64"/>
neceſſary for their Voyage, they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a neceſſity to part with it, for the preſervation of their lives.</p>
            <p>2. We have their Dangers as well as Endeavors. 1. It is expreſt in the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the Tempeſt; they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly toſſed with a Tempeſt. 2. It was dark weather, neither Sun nor Stars appeared, which uſed to be great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and helps to poor men at Sea. 3. Their Danger is expreſt in this, they were brought to the brink of the black pit of Deſpair; all Hope now was taken away. O what a ſad diſtreſſed condition was this! their Hope, which is called the Anchor of the Soul, yea which is the Sheet-Anchor of the Soul, was loſt; they gave all their lives over for gone and loſt: And oh, what could now a company of men do that had loſt their Hopes and Hearts? could theſe that had loſt their Hopes find their hands? they were now ſaying, as the Jews did in their Captivity, Our Hope is loſt, we are cut off for our parts, <hi>(Ezek.</hi> 37. 11.)</p>
            <p>3. We have their Deliverance and Preſervation, coming in at ſuch a time and ſeaſon as this was; now that they are brought to an extremity, God makes it his opportunity; and now that all hope
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:38362:65"/>
of being ſaved is taken away, ſalvation will be moſt ſeaſonable: and now the Angel appears to <hi>Paul,</hi> and tells him, all their lives are enſured, only the ſhip ſhall be loſt.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Obſervations are theſe:</head>
               <item>1. <hi>Dangers and Deliverances are to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully recorded and remembred; therefore</hi> Paul <hi>takes an account of both, here in this Voyage.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Salvations and Deliverances many times are not ſent, until perſons be left hopeleſs in themſelves.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I ſhall ſpeak a little to both theſe upon this preſent occaſion, that what you read here, may be remarked and remembred.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Dangers and Deliverances are to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully recorded and remembred. This Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation hath two parts: 1. Dangers are to be remembred. 2. Deliverances are to be remembred.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the Lords poor people uſed to do in all Ages: When <hi>Jacob</hi> was in danger of his Brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> you ſee how he comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morates it, and gives us an exact narrative of it, and tells us how he feared him:
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:38362:65"/>
               <hi>Lord, I fear my Brother</hi> Eſau, <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 34. 4.) How often was <hi>David</hi> in danger by <hi>Saul,</hi> who was his ſworn Enemy? and how many Pſalms have we, taking occaſion to remember what danger he was in, and how comfortably he was brought off: <hi>I ſought the Lord, and he heard me; and delivered me out of all my fears.</hi> (2 Cor. 1. 9, 10.) As <hi>Paul</hi> tells the Corinthians what danger they were in; they were preſt out of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, out of ſtrength, in ſo much that they deſpaired of life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſo at Sea as well as Land, he would have dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers remembred; how that they go up to the Heaven one while, and ſink into the deeps another; their Soul melted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of trouble, and they at their wits ends, <hi>&amp;c. Peter</hi>'s danger at Sea is record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when he began to ſink, and cried out, Maſter, ſave me, or I periſh, <hi>(Matth.</hi> 14. 28, 29, 30.) And the Diſciples, when they cried o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, <hi>Careſt thou not that we pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh?</hi> (Mark 4. 38.) It is obſerved the Ship now was full, and now comes ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and deliverance. Here was their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger recorded, the Ship was full, and Chriſt aſleep in the hinder part of the Ship.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Query is, How Dangers ſhould be remembred?</item>
               <item>2. How Deliverances ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred?</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:38362:66"/>
1. Dangers ſhould be remembred, conſidering we may come into them again. Many when dangers are not, they ſing to their Souls that ſong, and delude themſelves, The bitterneſs of Death is paſt; they think they are out of one ſtrom, and they ſhall never come in ſuch another. Juſt as perſons do with their Sickneſs at Land, ſo many do with their Dangers at Sea, if God bring them off: O they grow hardned and ſecure again. But if God hath brought home one dangerous Voyage, we ſhould think, it may be the next will be as dangerous; Have I eſcaped one at Sea, one at Land? if I do not improve it, if I do not walk ſuitable under it, O how eaſily can God bring me into another. You never were in ſuch Dangers, but you may come to the like again, whether at Sea or Land.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Dangers ſhould be remembred with conſideration to the greatneſs of them; great things ſhould be remembred, a great God, great Mercies, great Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances, great Sins, and great Dangers. How ſhould we think, O what a Danger was I in at this time by ſuch a Storm at Sea! by ſuch a Sickneſs aſhore! not only my Life in danger, but Lord, was not my Soul in danger? was I fit to die at
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:38362:66"/>
ſuch a time? had I gotten an intereſt in Chriſt, if I had been caſt away at ſuch a time? Men think dangers great for their Bodies, but they do not think them ſo for their Souls; they think them great for their Ships, for their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, but they do not think them ſo for their Eternal conditions; O, had not my Body, Soul, Ship, and all periſhed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. And was not this a great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? thy Souls danger was the greateſt danger; hadſt thou been drowned at ſuch a time, thy Soul had been ſhipwrackt to all Eternity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Dangers ſhould be remembred with conſideration to their ſuddenneſs; how many times do they come ſuddenly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us? As there is ſudden fear, ſo there is ſudden danger. When the Lord ſends the Winds out of his Treaſury ſuddenly, and threatens men at Sea with ſudden deſtruction, when deſolation ſeems to come as a Whirl-wind, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we ſhould think, What if ſudden death had come upon me, what a condition was my poor Soul in? what a dreadful thing would it have been if I had been ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed on a ſudden, and ſent into an Eternal condition, in the twinkling of an eye? I, to be threatned to be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:38362:67"/>
up, only with a formal God have mercy upon thee in thy mouth; not to have time to pray, repent, reflect upon thy paſt life: O what a ſad thing is this?</p>
            <p n="4">4. We ſhould think of our Danger with conſideration to the frames of our heart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what frames of heart we were then under. 1. To the frames of our hearts when in our dangers. 2. The frames of our hearts when brought from under them. 1. The frames of the heart when in and under them: were not you under great fears and hurries of Soul? it may be, not knowing how it would go with your Souls, if you had gone off the ſtage of this life at the preſent. <hi>David</hi> when he was in danger, took eſpecial notice of the frame of his ſpirit; <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable evils have compaſſed me about.</hi> (Pſal. 40. 12. 13.) He was compaſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout on every ſide with danger; and how was it with him then? he calls to mind, <hi>Mine iniquities have taken hold upon me, ſo that I am not able to look up,</hi> 57. 7.) And what then? O ſee how he prays<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Be pleaſed, O Lord, to deliver me; O Lord make haſt to help me.</hi> Remember what the frames of our hearts were in our dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, in reference to our fears; and ſecondly, what in reference to our faith
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:38362:67"/>
ſo alſo did <hi>David,</hi> when purſued in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by <hi>Saul. My heart is fixed, my heart is fixed; I will ſing and give praiſe.</hi> We are to remember our fears under our dangers, that we may be prepared better for future tryals; we are to remember our faith under dangers paſt, that we may be encouraged for the time to come in after ſtraits.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We are to remember our frames of ſpirit when God brings us out of our dangers; how then we were melted with the preſent ſenſe of the mercy; as thoſe Iſraelites, when God brought them out of danger, they believed God, they ſang and gave praiſe; O what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions were there then upon the Soul to be given up anew to God; to walk be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord in the light of the living. Thus alſo did <hi>David,</hi> when brought out of danger; <hi>Thy vows are upon me, O God,</hi> &amp;c. and at another time, <hi>The Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth the ſimple: I was brought low,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and thou helpedſt me,</hi> (Pſal. 56. 12, 13.) And then what a frame of heart was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him? <hi>Return unto thy reſt, O my Soul,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 116. 6, 7.) Then he was all for returning to God: O now there was freſh endearments betwixt the Soul and God. Theſe we are to remember, that
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:38362:68"/>
we may not wear totally the ſenſe of them off our ſpirits.</p>
            <p>5. We ſhould remember our dangers, with conſideration to the frequency of them; how frequently we were in them. <hi>Paul</hi> remembred this, in Perils by Sea often, in Perils by the Heathen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 26.) O how often have we been near Drowning, near Taking, near Sink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, near Dying, and yet God brought us off; theſe things we ſhould call to mind often; go out upon dangerous Voyages, and often come home; the oftner and more frequent our dangers, the more ſhould we think upon them.</p>
            <p>2. We ſhould Remember our Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, but how? 1. We ſhould Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them, ſo as to admire them; thus did the people of the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Ezra, Who hath given them ſuch deliverance as this?</hi> O! they admire it, and write a Non-ſuch upon the Head of it, as <hi>David</hi> admired the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, when he had ſpoken of his Houſe to come. Is this the manner of men, O God? He was in an holy Extaſy of Heavenly admiration; ſo ſhould you ſay now; to carry out, and bring home, in ſuch a dangerous time as this; To hide from Enemies, when ſought for in ſuch a time ſuch a Voyage as this: Oh! <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:38362:68"/>
am I? And what is my Fathers houſe, that he ſhould bring me hitherto?</hi> You ſhould turn the Deliverance on every ſide, and admire the goodneſs of God, the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, the mercy of God, the power of God, the faithfulneſs of God in it, and ſay, O Lord, what a Deliverance is this? What a Voyage is this? God loves to have his Mercies admired by us.</p>
            <p>2. We ſhould Remember our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, to have our Hearts raiſed up in gratitude, and thankfulneſs to God for them; Thus did <hi>David, I will pay my Vows unto the Lord, in preſence of all his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: I will take the Cup of Salvation, and call upon the Name of the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 116. 12, 13, 14. We are to remember to pay our Thank-offerings unto God, after our Deliverance from God: What, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get ſuch a Deliverance as this? What, not be thankful for ſuch a Preſervation as this?</p>
            <p>3. We ſhould Remember our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, ſo as to endear our Hearts to God; Thus we find <hi>David, I will love thee, O Lord, I will love the Lord dearly,</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Heb.) <hi>The Lord is my Rock, my Fortreſs, and my Deliverer,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. 1. O! now how ſhould Souls, after their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance; boil, and burn in Love to God!
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:38362:69"/>
How are we engaged to a Friend that is at any time but an Inſtrument in God's hand to Deliver us? And ſhall we be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared to the Inſtrument, and not to the Author? O! How was <hi>David</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared to God, when he ſaid, <hi>He having Redeemed him, he would walk before the Lord in the Land of the Living,</hi> Pſal. 56. <hi>ult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. We ſhould Remember our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances to improve them in a way of acting Faith, when the next danger and ſtraits comes: <hi>I will remember thee from the Land of Jordan, from the Hill</hi> Miſſar, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42. 6, 7. This was to encourage him from his former Deliverances in his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtraits and exigencies. What, now diſtruſt God, who hath delivered in ſix Troubles, and now ſhall we give way to Unbelief in the Seventh? Did not holy <hi>David</hi> thus? <hi>He hath delivered me out of the Paw of the Lyon, and out of the Paw of the Bear, and he will deliver me out of the hand of the uncircumciſed Philiſtine.</hi> Thus <hi>Paul</hi> remembers his Deliverance from <hi>Nero. And I was delivered out of the mouth of the Lyon, and the Lord ſhall delive me from every evil work,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 17, 18.</p>
            <p>5. We ſhould remember our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, to be often inculcating, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printing
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:38362:69"/>
them upon our own hearts: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, when we receive them, they are a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle freſh it may be upon our ſpirits, but O how ſoon do they die, becauſe they are not written upon our hearts; they are not Engraven there as a Man that would Remember a thing, be it a Notion, or any Reſolution, he will be often turning it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in his thoughts; Alas, if we write our Deliverances, Is it not in the Duſt? whereas we ſhould write them in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: We ſhould write them with a Pen of Iron, and the point of a Diamond.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We ſhould Commemorate our Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers with our Deliverances, becauſe God gives them to that end. The Lord doth not give us our Deliverances to caſt them at our heels, nor brings us out of our Dangers, that we might forget them, as tho we had never been in any of them. God expects that we ſhould faithfully Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter and Record them; therefore it was a great Provocation to the Lord, that the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſo ſoon forgot his works: If you do but forget the kindneſs of a Friend, you think it is diſingenious; but O then, What is it to forget that God that hath delivered you out of ſix trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and in ſeven troubles? God loves and expects his kindneſs ſhould be kept upon Record.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:38362:70"/>
2. We ſhould Commemorate our Dangers and Deliverances, becauſe it was freely of his grace to bring us out of the one, and put us under the other; Is it not of his meer mercy that he reſcu'd and pull'd us out of our dangers? Might not we elſe been ſwallow'd up of them? And may not we all ſay in this caſe, as the Pſalmiſt in that? <hi>Had it not been the Lord who was on our ſide then, the waters had overwhelmed us, the ſtream had gone o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our Soul, then the proud Waves had gone over our Soul,</hi> Pſal. 124. 4, 5. May not you who have been ſo often deliver'd at Sea in eminent dangers ſing this Song<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> What, and now forget ſuch dangers? and caſt behind your backs ſuch Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances. Oh! the freer any favour is, the more it ſhould be remembred; Doth God ſee any thing in us, or in our Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, more then others, to beſtow ſuch deliverances for? One Man goes to Sea, and he is taken; another goes to Sea, and he is ſunk; another goes to Sea, and he dies the Term of the Voyage; And why doth the Lord preſerve you? Is not this Free-Grace? not becauſe you are more Righteous, but becauſe he is more Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious; And ſhould not this be Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred?</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:38362:70"/>
3. Our Dangers and Deliverances ſhould be remembred, becauſe God hath gracious ends and deſigns both in the one and the other; What ends hath God to bring us into dangers? 1. He by this hath an end and deſign to quicken up to duty; it may be there may be ſome omitted duty; neglected duties often bring Men into great and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent dangers; it may be a Perſon is convinced of the duty of Prayer, but it may be neglected; Oh then God will bring into danger to quicken to duty; Oh, ſays God, <hi>In their affliction they will ſeek me early.</hi> The very Heathen Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners called out for Prayer in time of danger. Obſerve it, that Perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of duties, either Perſonal or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtical, and yet neglected, God uſually whips them to their Duties, by one dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, affliction or another. The Proverb is good, if you would teach a Man to Pray, ſend him to Sea. 2. God by bringing us into dangers, hath a deſign upon us to convince us of ſin; many Convictions hath come into the Soul at this door; Dangers have often proved inlets to Convictions. Oh! What Convictions have many poor Souls lain under while in danger, when it may be the dangers hath
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:38362:71"/>
given them a view of Eternity; when Dangers hath preſented Death to the Man, and Conſcience hath cried, Now thou art ſinking, now there is but a ſtep betwixt thee and Eternity, betwixt thee and another World? Oh then what Convictions hath the Soul lyen under? and yet it may be when the Danger is over, the Conviction is over too. Well, though we may forget all, yet God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members all. 3. God hath a deſign up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us in our Dangers, to prepare us for our latter end. The danger thou art in, and hath eſcaped, calls for to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for thy Death, which muſt certainly come to paſs ſhortly. God by Dangers would have you prepare for Death: And Oh! VVhat a cutting Conſideration will this be when thou com'ſt to die? that thou who haſt been in ſo many dangers by Sea and Land, ſhould have no more learned to die, nor ready to die. Alas, you eſcaped the laſt, that you might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for the next. 4. God hath a deſign upon our Graces by bringing us into dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; Danger is to exert and draw forth Grace. Thus the Diſciples Dangers at Sea were to draw forth their Faith. Faith and Patience comes moſt viſibly upon the ſtage in times of moſt eminent danger.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:38362:71"/>
5. God by bringing us into Dangers, hath a deſign upon our Souls; he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by danger of drowning the Body, hath ſaved the Soul, and hath cauſed it to ſay, <hi>Periiſſem niſi periiſsem:</hi> I had pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, if I had not periſhed. Some have eſcaped Shipwrack of Soul, by Shipwrack of Body; And ſhall we forget ſuch Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, when God hath ſuch gracious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns in them upon us?</p>
            <p>2. He drives on gracious ends and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns in our Deliverances, And ſhall we then forget them? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1. He ſpares us, that we may account his long-ſuffering Salvation; he gives, by ſparing of us, ſpace to Repent; and Oh! What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> dreadful thing is it not to remember wherefore we are ſpared and delivered? <hi>He gave her ſpace to Repent, but ſhe repented not,</hi> Pſal. 56. <hi>ult.</hi> The Priſoner is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieved, that he might ſue out his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, And will he forget the end for which he is Reprieved? 2. He delivers, that we may live to him. Why was <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s feet deliver'd from falling? it was, that he might walk before the Lord in the light of the living. He gives us our lives, that we might give them back again to God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. 10. Men are not deliver'd from dangers to live to themſelves, to
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:38362:72"/>
live to their luſts, to Drink, and Swear, and Rant, and Roar, as a great many poor Wretches do. That ſay as they did, <hi>We are deliver'd to do all theſe abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,</hi> Pſal. 50. 15. 3. God hath ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end in Deliverance, that we might glorifie him, in paying our Vows to him. <hi>I will deliver thee;</hi> And what then when out of Trouble never remember it more, caſt it behind thy back; O no; <hi>And thou ſhalt glorifie me.</hi> He aims at a revenue of glory out of your deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. 4. God hath another end in deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering of us; that we might enter into New Engagements, to be more the Lords; as in times of great dangers, there uſe to be great engagements betwixt God and the Soul; ſo in times of Great Deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, there are great Engagements paſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and the Soul, New Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to God; New Deliverances call for New Dedications of the Soul to God; now the Soul ſhould be ſet apart for God more than ever. 5. God hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother end in delivering of us, that we might break off our league with ſin; thus it was with them, <hi>Shall we break his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, after ſuch great deliverance as this?</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:38362:72"/>
               <head>APPLICATION.</head>
               <p>Is it ſo, that our Dangers and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances ſhould be remembred by us? then it is a word of Information.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Learn we here how acceptable it is to God, that we thankfully congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late our Mercies. No Muſick like a ſound of Trumpets off the VVaters: ſo, O what ſweet Muſick doth it make in God's Eares, that you thankfully record Sea-Mercies, and Sea-Deliverances; this is Muſick of the VVaters; this makes Melody in God's Eares. Sea-Prayers and Sea-Praiſes come up acceptably be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord; he is ſo pleaſed with them, that he hath called them Sacrifices. O that Men would offer the Sacrifice of Praiſe; this is the found of Trumpets you ſhould carry to Sea with you, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bound, and homeward bound.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Learn we hence what a Great E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil it is to loſe the remembrance of our Dangers and Deliverances. VVhat do many Families? VVhat do many Perſons with the Sea-Dangers, with the Sea-Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances? Do not they write them in the duſt? Do not they bury them in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Oblivion? Do not they caſt
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:38362:73"/>
them behind their backs? Do not they trample them under foot? O poor Souls! they little know what they do. 1. Such Deliverances will have a Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in their Conſciences one day; though they bury them now, O they will riſe again: And Oh! How will they then dread and terrifie a poor Soul? 2. Such Deliverances will another day be witneſſes and evidences againſt you. Oh! VVhat a cutting teſtimony will they give in againſt the Soul? Haſt not thou been graciouſly and wonderfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in ſuch a Voyage, in ſuch a Storm at Sea, in ſuch a Sickneſs at Shore, and yet walked unſuitably under all thefe? To be caſt out by mercy, O what a dreadful thing is this! 3. Such deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances forgotten by us, harden us; either they ſoften or harden. Theſe Providences are like God's Ordinances in this reſpect, they either harden or ſoften. Oh! VVhat a dreadful thing it is to be harden'd by Deliverances and Preſervation, and yet many are. <hi>Sentence being not ſpeedily executed, the hearts of Men are fully ſet in them to do evil.</hi> 4. Such Deliverances will be Great aggravations both of man's ſin and miſery, if forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by them. The goodneſs of God
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:38362:73"/>
was the aggravation of the ſin of <hi>David,</hi> ſays God, <hi>When I had done ſo and ſo for thee, nay, and I would have done more, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haſt thou deſpiſed the Commandment of the Lord, to do evil in his ſight,</hi> 2 Sam. 12. 8, 9. VVhat, for you that had ſuch deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances as theſe, to break his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; as <hi>Ezra</hi> ſays; O this is an high aggravation! 5. Deliverances and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers forgotten will cauſe the Lord to pull in his hand in a way of mercy, will cauſe God to give up Perſons, and take his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting Preſence from them, take them from the ſhadow of his VVings. Souls by forgetting paſt dangers and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, may put themſelves from under God's Protection for the future.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Is it ſo that we are to Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our Sea-dangers and deliverances? then it is a word of Exhortation; be exhorted then to call to mind, and keep in mind, what God hath done for you; and in this Exhortation I addreſs my ſelf to Sea-faring men, whoſe lives are a courſe and ſeries of VVonders in their frequent Salvations and Preſervations, (witneſs this Treatiſe) as you ſee the wonders of God in the Deeps, <hi>(viz.)</hi> The wonders of his Creation, ſo do you ſee the wonders of his Salvation:
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:38362:74"/>
How often may <hi>Wonderful</hi> be Written upon the Head of Salvations that you are every Voyage receiving from God? you never go out, and come home, but God works <hi>Wonderfully,</hi> and appears <hi>Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> for you; Is not he a Wonder-working-God for you every Voyage?</p>
               <p>The Exhortation is to call to mind, and keep in mind, to Record and Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter your Dangers and Deliverances, and not to do as <hi>Iſrael</hi> is ſaid to do, who ſoon forgot his Works. How often doth God bring in this ſin of theirs in one <hi>Pſalm?</hi> They forgot his works, and the wonders he had ſhewed them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. 13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. 11.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Keep them in mind, for they are wonderful Dangers and Deliverances; They are Wonders, theſe are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred. <hi>Marvellous thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s did he for them, in the ſight of their Fathers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He devided the Sea, and cauſed them to paſs through, and he made the waters to ſtand as an heap, Pſal.</hi> 78. 12, 13. And it is brought in again in that <hi>Pſalm. They remembred not his hand, nor the day when God delivered them out of the hand of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal..</hi> 73. 42. And in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y forgot God their Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, which had done great things in Egypt,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:38362:74"/>
Wondrous works in the Land of</hi> Ham, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. 21. 22. This heightens the ſin exceedingly to forget ſuch Great and Wonderful Dangers and Deliverances.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Your Dangers are Wonderful in this Reſpect, they are often ſuch as threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a ſentence of Death to be executed upon you. May it not be ſaid of poor Sea-men, as was of them; <hi>For we would not (Brethren) have you ignorant of our trouble, which came to us in</hi> Aſia, <hi>that we were preſſed out of meaſure, above ſtrength, inſomuch that we deſpaired of Life, but we had the ſentence of death in our ſelves, that we ſhould not truſt in our ſelves, but in him that raiſeth the dead, who deliverid us from ſo great a Death, and doth Deliver,</hi> 2 Cor. 1. 8, 9, 10. O how many Sea-faring Men may ſay thus! Our Dangers have been ſuch, as we have often deſpaired of Life; there hath but been a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us and Death; nay, betwixt us and Eternity; And ſhall we forget ſuch dangers, when we have been ſo near death in them? As he ſaid to <hi>David, As the Lord lives, there is but one ſtep betwixt thee and death.</hi> O how often have you been near ſinking, near drowning, and yet God hath then appeared for you, with an outſtretched Arm, and in the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:38362:75"/>
Mount hath been ſeen, And will you not remember this?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Your Dangers are Wonderful in this Reſpect, they are ſudden and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing, they are wonderfully ſudden; How are you often, all on a ſudden, threatned with nothing but preſent Death and Deſtruction? It may be ſaid of Sea-men, as of thoſe in <hi>Job, Snares compaſſes them about, and ſudden fear trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth them,</hi> Job 22. 10. It doth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trouble them, but all on a ſudden trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them, before they know almoſt where they are (as we ſay;) VVe read of ſome whoſe Calamity ſhall come ſuddenly. <hi>Suddenly ſhall he be broken without Remedy,</hi> Prov. 6. 15. O how terrible is ſuch a caſe, or ſuch a danger And hath not God often threatned to make this your caſe and condition? O then do not forget ſuch dangers that have ſo ſuddenly lookt you in the Face!</p>
               <p n="3">3. Your Dangers are VVonderful in this Reſpect, they are not Dangers in which your Bodies are concerned only, but they are Dangers in which your Souls are concerned; It is not only the danger of a Ship-wrack'd Veſſel, and a Ship-wrack'd Eſtate, and a Shipwrack'd Body, but a Shipwrack'd Soul. Here
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:38362:75"/>
is the great danger, leſt thou make a loſt Voyage for thy Soul: If thou had died in ſuch a Storm, or died in the Term of ſuch a Voyage; Oh! VVhat would have become of thy Soul, thy precious, thy immortal Soul? Had not thou died in a Carnal, in a Chriſtleſs ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition? Had not thy poor Soul periſh'd to all Eternity, if thou then had miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried? VVas not thou then a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger altogether to Chriſt, and a VVork of Saving Grace upon thy Heart? Had not thou then the guilt of all thy ſins upon the back of thy Soul unpardoned? And O what danger was this! And wilt thou forget ſuch dangers?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Your Dangers are ſuch at Sea, as none but a God can deliver from; all your skill cannot; O, then is the greateſt Artiſt at his Wits end! The Pſalmiſt tells us, <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 107. 27.) the Marriners in their Storms, are at their wits end; (or as ſome read it) all their wiſdom is ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up, they know not what courſe to Steer, (the <hi>Dutch</hi> Annorators carry it,) Now their very Pilots are at a loſs; Now all their courage cannot contribute to their deliverance, though men of the greateſt natural courage and magnanimity in the world: Yet now their hearts melt
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:38362:76"/>
becauſe of troubles; as it is ſaid of the Marriners in <hi>Jonahs</hi> Ship, <hi>The Marriners were afraid.</hi> O now, when Death and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, the Grave and Judgment to come looks them in the face! Then they are <hi>Magor-Miſſabibs,</hi> terror to themſelves, and to all about them; O now, the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is ſuch, it muſt be the only finger of God that can help! I have heard of a Ship in <hi>Yarmouth</hi> Road, that in a great Storm, they feared the Anchor would come home, and the Maſter diſcourſing with a Youth in the Ship, that God had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun lately to work ſome Convictions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, O ſays he, Maſter if God do but lay a Finger upon one Strand of the Cable, it will hold; and in the morning many Ships were loſt near them, and there was but one Strand in the Cable left. O the finger of God only can ſometimes ſave in dangers. It was a good ſaying of a Godly Commander of a Ship in eminent dangers, <hi>None now but that God that ſaved the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Iſrael <hi>at the Red Sea, can ſave us out of this diſtreſs;</hi> and as ſoon as he had ſaid it, the Wind altered, and ſaved them; And will you forget ſuch dangers as none but a God can ſave from?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Your dangers at Sea are ſuch as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands have periſhed in; how many
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:38362:76"/>
have gone to Sea, that never returned more? that have been ſwallowed up in the belly of the great Deeps? How many have periſhed by the Sword at Sea? how many by violent Storms? and that God ſhould put a difference betwixt you and others, and you ſhould forget it, this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly heightens and aggravates the guilt. How many have loſt their lives? how many have loſt their limbs? and yet in ſuch dangers God hath brought you off; this is never to be forgotten.</p>
               <p>2. Your dangers are not only wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but your deliverances are ſo too, and therefore ſhould be remembred. There is never a deliverance, but you may read a wonder in it; ſo many deliverances and ſalvations at Sea, ſo many wonders. God ſaves you in a miraculous way.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Is not this a wonder, that perſons of ſuch great ſins and provocations, ſhould be perſons of ſuch great ſalvations and preſervations? that ſuch as ſin every Voyage, nay, it may be at an high rate ſin every Voyage, ſhould be ſaved and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered at ſuch an high rate every Voyage? is not this a wonder, that men of ſuch ſins, ſhould be men of ſuch ſalvations? that men that ſin againſt theſe ſalvations, ſhould not have theſe deliverances ſhorten
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:38362:77"/>
upon them. Oh what a wonder is this! We ſhould wonder if a perſon ſhould be continually diſobliging any of us, and yet we ſhould be ſtill heaping up kindneſſes upon him: This made the Prophet <hi>Ezra</hi> ſay, <hi>Shall we again break his Commandments, after ſuch deliverance as this?</hi> O do not you provoke the Lord every time that you go out, and ſtill he delivers you, ſtill he returns you to your Relations, to viſit your habitations in peace! and is not this a wonder?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Your deliverances are wonderful, if you conſider your deliverances are great deliverances. We read of ſuch; <hi>And the Lord ſaved them with a great deliverance;</hi> or with a great ſalvation. Thus ſaid <hi>Sampſon, Thou haſt given this great deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance into the hand of thy ſervant,</hi> (Judg. 15. 18.) Now any great tranſactions are remembred and recorded. Your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances are great, if we conſider theſe things; 1. They are commanded deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances by the great God; his word of command brings all our deliverances a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, whether at Sea or Land. Which made the Church in diſtreſs pray, <hi>Thou art my King, O God, command deliverances for</hi> Jacob, <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 44. 4.) He commands every thing tending to deliverance at Sea; in order to deliverance, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:38362:77"/>
the Winds; <hi>He maketh the ſtorm a calm,</hi> (Pſal. 107. 29.) He alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the Seas; he ſays to the proud Waves, <hi>So far, and no farther.</hi> You read of a decree ſet to the Sea, that it cannot paſs; <hi>Though the Waves thereof toſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet can they not prevail; though they roar, yet can they not paſs over it,</hi> (Jer. 5. 22.) It is the great God only that rides Lord Admiral at Sea, to command the Seas and the Waves thereof. God is ſaid to ſhut up the Sea with doors, and ſet bars upon it. <hi>Hitherto ſhalt thou come, and no further; and here ſhall thy proud waves be ſtayed,</hi> (Job. 38. 8, 11.) <hi>Xerxes</hi> preſumed he could tame the <hi>Helleſpont,</hi> for attempting his Bridge of Boats; but all this was in vain, this is a flower in Gods Crown alone, to command the Sea. Your deliverances are a fruit and effect of Gods commanding Power, therefore great. 2. They are great deliverances, as they are the curious workmanſhip (as I may call them) of the Attributes of a great God. Deliverance is ſaid to be wrought for us, it is the handy work of God; <hi>If God will work, who can let?</hi> (as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43. 13, 14.) And he ſeems to ſpeak it upon the account of the deliverance of his People; <hi>For your ſake I have ſent down to</hi> Babylon, <hi>and have
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:38362:78"/>
brought down all their Nobles, and the</hi> Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans, <hi>whoſe cry is in their ſhips.</hi> In every deliverance there is the excellent work of the Attributes of God; we may in ſuch a deliverance ſay, Here is the Power of God, and here is the Wiſdom of God, and here is the Love of God, and here is the Faithfulneſs of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For as God in the confounding of the Languages at <hi>Babel,</hi> ſaid, <hi>Go too, let us go down,</hi> (as if he derected himſelf to his glorious Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, compaſſing about his glorious Throne) <hi>Come, let us go down.</hi> Gen. 11. 7. (Or, as ſome take it of the Trinity, as in the Creation.) So when God ſends us deliverances in our diſtreſſes, he ſets his Attributes at work; Go Power, go Mercy, go Love, go Faithfulneſs, go and act your reſpective parts in this deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; and muſt not this be then an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and curious Piece that Gods At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes bring forth? 3. They are great deliverances, if we conſider the great ſins and provocations they come over the heads of, the great unworthineſs of the receiver, heightens much the mercy and favour received; the reaſon why perſons do not greaten their deliverances, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not greaten their ſins, in the deep ſenſe and aggravations of them.
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:38362:78"/>
O ſuch a Soul would ſay, as <hi>David, Is this the manner of men?</hi> O God, is not this a great deliverance for ſuch a great ſinner to receive? 4. They are great deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, if we conſider the time and ſeaſon of their coming in; as this deliverance of the Ships Company where <hi>Paul</hi> was, it was when all hope of being ſaved was taken away; and ſo were many of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances mentioned in this Treatiſe. So <hi>Peter</hi>'s Sea-deliverance, when he began to ſink, Chriſt ſtretched forth his hand immediately; he was now ſinking and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but ſee how ready Chriſt was to ſave; <hi>He ſtretched forth his hand and caught</hi> Peter, <hi>(Matth.</hi> 14. 28, 29, 30.) Our ſinking time, is Jeſus Chriſts ſaving time. In the Mount is the Lord ſeen; our extremity is Gods opportunity; and are not then theſe great deliverances never to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten? 5. They are great deliverances, if we conſider they are not only deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of Bodies, and Ships, and Eſtates ſometimes, but Souls; and where the Ship is loſt, and the Eſtate is loſt, yet for the life to be ſaved, and the Soul deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is a very great Deliverance; a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieve when a Priſoner is under the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Death, is a great Mercy: O when God Reprieves a poor Priſoner,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:38362:79"/>
this is ſome Deliverance; we read o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome Deliverance God gave to <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the days of <hi>Shiſhak;</hi> a Reprieve is ſome Deliverance, but if it end in ſuing out the Priſoners Pardon, then it is a great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance. If it be ſuch a Deliverance in a Storm at Sea, as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had from a Sickneſs at Shoar, <hi>Thou haſt delivered me in love to my Soul, and caſt all my ſins behind thy back,</hi> (Iſa. 38.) This is a double De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, and ſure ſuch Deliverances as theſe are worth Recording; Theſe are to be written in Marble and not in Duſt, with the Pen of Iron, (as the Prophet ſays) and not with with point of a Diamond.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Your Deliverances are wonderful, if you conſider the many thouſands that have periſhed in leſs Dangers to an eye of Reaſon; they are diſtinguiſhing Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, and therefore wonderful hath God dealt with all men that go to Sea as with you. Hath not thouſands periſhed by the Sword at Sea in bloody Engagements? Miſcarried at Sea in dreadful and terrible Storms; Hath not the Sea been a Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher for thouſands? Are not there Millions of the Dead that the Sea muſt one day give up, and yet you Delivered, and yet you ſpared? O what diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mercy is this! And ſhall this be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:38362:79"/>
by you? Should not you keep Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of diſtinguiſhing Mercy? How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſunk ſometimes, and periſhed by your ſides? How many that went out with you that never Returned? One taken, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other left; one ſunk, and another ſaved.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Your Deliverances are Wonderful, if you conſider the way that ſometimes God takes to bring them about; O what ſtrange ways doth God take to deliver, when he hath a mind to deliver; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he brings down to the very Gate of the Grave, he brings to the Doors and Bars of the Sea, and then ſhuts theſe doors; as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, He brings to the next door to periſhing, and then he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers; <hi>Maſter ſave me, or I periſh;</hi> and then he lends an Arm, witneſs many of theſe deliverances here mentioned. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he doth it by ſtrange means, low and contemptible, as the poor man that we Read of, that delivered the City, <hi>(Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 15.) ſometimes by unthought of and unexpected means, as he that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved Major <hi>Gibbons,</hi> as this Story men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he was a <hi>French</hi> Pyrate. As that Ship I have heard off, that when ſhe ſprang a Leak, and they all had like to have periſhed, all on a ſudden the Leak ſtopt, and they knew no Reaſon, but when they
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:38362:80"/>
came into the next Port to ſearch her, there was a great Fiſh had wrought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the Leak, that they were glad to cut him out; was not here a miraculous deliverance? That <hi>Jonah</hi> ſhould be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up by the Whale, O what a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle was this! and ſo he was preſerved! and how have ſome been ſaved by ſudden ſhifts of Winds when near ſinking and periſhing? theſe are to be remembred to the Lord while you live: Oh! methinks this one Motive ſhould ſet on the Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, if I ſhould uſe no more, to Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber your Dangers and your Deliverances.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, another Motive is this, to Remember your Dangers with your Deliverances; this will in your great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes and extremities, contribute ſome hope to you; to read over your Regiſter, your ancient Records, how good God hath been at ſuch a time, and ſuch a time; how ſeaſonably he ſtept in and delivered in ſuch a ſtrait and ſuch a ſtrait; Oh then ſays the Soul, why ſhould I deſpair, and caſt off all hope now? hath not he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared and ſaved in Deaths often before now? for paſt experiences are good ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports for Hope in preſent exigencies and extremities; thus <hi>David</hi> argues, when at a great ſtrait, <hi>Thou haſt delivered me, and
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:38362:80"/>
wilt deliver me;</hi> and thus <hi>Paul, Thou haſt delivered me, and wilt deliver me. Haman</hi> found this a good way to Remember the years of the Lords right hand.</p>
               <p>3. Remember your Dangers and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances, for God Records them; they are filled up by God, and he will mind you of them another day if you forget them now; he keeps his Journals and Records; he hath his Book of Remembrance of your forgotten Mercies, as well as your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſins; God will one day read over all thoſe Deliverances you have forgotten; Oh poor Soul! did not I deliver thee in ſuch a Danger, in ſuch a Diſtreſs, in ſuch a Death, when there was no Hope, when there was no Help, yet all this haſt thou forgotten; forgotten thy Mercy, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten the God of thy Mercy; Oh! will not this ſting you to the Heart, when God ſhall cauſe your ſtrangled, and murdered Mercies to walk in your Conſciences? when he ſhall give them a Reſurrection there?</p>
               <p>4. Motive to Remember your Dangers and Deliverances: the Vows of God are upon you; Oh! what did you ſay to God in the day of your diſtreſs and calamity? Lord, if thou wilt now appear, and be a preſent help in time of trouble, it ſhall
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:38362:81"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:38362:81"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:38362:82"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:38362:82"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:38362:83"/>
never be forgotten, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall be remembred to the Lord as long as we have a day to live; but when God brings poor Souls off, many do not only forget their Vows, but deny them; In Ancient times it was uſual in eminent dangers, whether at Sea or Land, to make Vows; We read that <hi>Jonahs</hi> Mariners they Vowed Vows, <hi>(Jonah</hi> 1. 16.) <hi>David</hi> did thus, <hi>Thy Vows are upon me, O God! I will render praiſes unto thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56 11. (and in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place) <hi>I will pay thee my Vows, which my lips have uttered, and my mouth hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken when I was in trouble,</hi> (Pſal. 66. 13, 14.) But becauſe this is ſo ordinary to make Vows at Sea, and brake them a Shoar, let me enlarge a little upon it. 1. Why ſhould you forget your Vows after your Deliverances? They were not raſh Vows, there might have been ſome excuſe, if you had made them raſhly, you might then have had a Plea, for ſaying it was an Error; but in times of diſtreſs, men are ſerious, when Death and Eternity is ſet before them, and they upon the brink of another world; dare you ſinners raſhly Vow, in this day of your diſtreſs; O no, your Conſciences will bear witneſs againſt you, that you were in ſober-ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at that day. 2. Why ſhould you
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:38362:83"/>
forget your Vows after your Deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for God will require payment? Nay, this is not only the Reaſon why we ſhould not forget to pay, but why we ſhould not delay to pay; <hi>When thou vows a vow to the Lord thy God, thou ſhouldſt not ſlack to pay it, for the Lord thy God will require it, yea, will ſurely require it of thee, and is would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſin in thee,</hi> (Deut. 23. 21.) Take it for granted he will do it, yea, he will ſurely do it. 1. He will require it, ſo as to call to a payment day, he will demand it, he will ſend unto you a Summons to pay the Vows you made to him in the day of your Diſtreſs. Oh! how often is Conſcience Gods Officer, that he ſends to you to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Payment? O ſays Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ience, Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, pay what thou oweſt to the God of thy deliverances; is not he a God to whom the Vows muſt be performed? 2. He will require it, ſo as to puniſh the non-payment; and ſo requiring is here taken, and in many other places, the Lord doth very often ſeverely puniſh Vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaking; breaking of Vows doth cauſe God often to deſtroy the works of your hands. Say not before the Angel, <hi>It was an error, wherefore ſhould God be angry at thy Vows, and deſtroy the works of thy hands?</hi> (Eccleſ. 5. 4, 5.) Some Expoſitors refer
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:38362:84"/>
this to the Prieſt, before whom the ſin of raſh vows was to be confeſt; others carry it to Chriſt, the Angel of the Covenant. who ſees through all our ſubtil excuſes and equivocations, and puniſhes them. O, God is angry when men go ſo flatly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Vows; O then God is angry, and deſtroys the work of their hands, <hi>viz.</hi> diſappoints their endeavours, and denies them ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, to forget your deliverances and dangers, is the greateſt ingratitude and unthankfulneſs in the world; hath God given you ſo many wonderful deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo many miraculous preſervations, to be buried in the grave of oblivion? will you murder your mercies, and then bury them? It is commonly ſaid, Murder will out. Murdered Mercies will one day make terrible work, in walking in your Conſciences.</p>
               <p>The next Obſervation is this, That Salvations and Deliverances many times are not ſent until perſons be left helpleſs and hopeleſs. I ſhall give you a touch of this. Now all hope of being ſaved was taken away, no ſmall tempeſt lay upon them; now they were gulft in deſpair of ever coming off with their lives: Yet this often is the condition of Nations,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:38362:84"/>
Ship-Companies, and Perſons, where God intends to ſave and deliver. The proofs of the laſt Obſervation about Dangers and Deliverances being recorded and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, proves this alſo. Thus was <hi>Peter</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, the Diſciples ſaved, when juſt at ſinking</p>
               <p>But why doth God ſtay ſo long before he ſends deliverances and ſalvations? 1. Becauſe he delights to draw forth a ſpirit of prayer; if men will not pray when ſinking, when drowning, when dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they will never pray. O ſee how <hi>Jonah</hi> prays in his diſtreſs: <hi>And</hi> Jonah <hi>prayed to the Lord out of the Fiſhes belly, and ſaid, I cried by reaſon of mine affliction unto the Lord, and he heard me; out of the belly of Hell cried I, and thou heardſt my voice,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>When my Soul fainted within me, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred the Lord; and my Prayer came in unto thy holy Temple,</hi> (Jonah 2. 1, 2, 3, 7.) O Sirs, God loves prayer ſo well; that he ſtayes with his deliverances, that we might ſue them out by prayer. <hi>Out of the Depths have I cried unto thee,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> (Pſal. 130. 1.) Driven to it by deep and bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs ſtraits, into which I am plunged. And it ſeems to be an alluſion to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners, in their diſtreſſes and dangers of being ſhipwrackt, crying unto the Lord. What will any man periſh, and never pray
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:38362:85"/>
Houſe, when he had ſo long been ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the Fields, with his Husks, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Swine!</p>
               <p>4. Becauſe God will have all his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Deliverances look like his own hand and arm, his own arm brings ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with him; he will have the print of his own hand upon it, that poor ſinners may ſay, <hi>This is the finger of God,</hi> the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God, <hi>and it is marvellous in our eyes.</hi> Alas, Men would attribute it to themſelves, if Salvation did not come in ſuch a way, when all hope of being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved is taken away. Oh! every thing is beautiful in its ſeaſon; Is not Salvation and Deliverance now in ſeaſon? now they begin to deſpair, as to probable or viſible hopes. O now God works like himſelf, now he appears in a deliverance to be God; which ſet the Diſciples a wondring, <hi>What manner of Man is this, that the Winds and Sea obey him?</hi> Mark 4. 41. And at another time, when he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd his Diſciples at Sea, and calmed the Winds, then they that were in the Ship worſhipped him, ſaying, <hi>Of a truth thou are the Son of God,</hi> Matth. 14. 32, 33.</p>
               <p>5. Becauſe he will by ſuch ſalvations ſet off his love to poor Souls: Was not the love of Chriſt ſet off highly, in taking
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:38362:85"/>
that ſeaſon to ſave the Ship when it was full; to ſave them when they were fink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; Is not that great Love, that ſteps forth to ſave in an Extremity? O what Love was this, to ſave this Ships Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, when all hope of being ſaved was taken away? Love always chuſes the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt times to appear and evidence it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Becauſe he will have his deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances, endearing deliverances to Souls. O how doth ſuch an appearance of God, at ſuch a time, endear the Soul of the Receiver. Therefore, ſaith <hi>David, I will love the Lord,</hi> (or love the Lord dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) <hi>my Rock and my Deliverer,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But I will proceed to give you alſo a taſte of the Application, and not be large, becauſe I have been large upon the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, which was mainly intended.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Then learn we hence, that God may for gracious ends, known to himſelf, delay a mercy or a deliverance, and yet fully intends to give in that mercy. <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> may wreſtle all night, and yet be put off; but in the break of day the mercy comes. The Woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> may cry to Chriſt for her Daughter, and at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent be put off, yet at laſt ſhe ſhall carry it. The believing Soul may not have
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:38362:86"/>
the Dove come with an Olive-branch in her Mouth until Evening. Chriſt's ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting of his love to poor Souls, is called his Supping with them; <hi>And I will ſup with you:</hi> Now ſupper comes not up till Evening.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Learn we hence, that God's timing our deliverances and ſalvations, is beſt for us; his time is the beſt time. Our time is always ready, (but ſaith Chriſt) My <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is not yet. If we had our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in our time, we ſhould not ſee that beauty in them; for every thing is beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful in its ſeaſon: and God chuſes the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſeaſons to ſeud them, becauſe he will put a beauty upon them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Learn we hence, that no caſe is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate to God, though it be ſo to Man: One would have thought this a deſperate caſe, in ſuch a Storm, lightning the Ship, the caſting out of the Tackling of the Ship, neither Sun nor Stars appeared, and all hope of being ſaved taken away; yet all this was but deſperate to them, it was not ſo to God: now their extremity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes God's opportunity, and he takes this juncture of time to appear in. Thus <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 42. 7, 8. all God's waves and God's billows had gone over him; a deſperate caſe! yet God (then he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves)
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:38362:86"/>
would command his loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the day-time, and his Song ſhould be with him in the Night. Faith is an excellent Grace at a deſperate ſtand.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Learn we hence, that God's thoughts are not as our thoughts; when we think of nothing but ſinking and periſhing, then doth God think of ſaving and delivering. They thought all hope of being ſaved was taken away, but God looks through the Storm and Cloud, and comforts them. As the Diſciples, when they thought it had been a Spirit in their Storm that appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them; No, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid; be of good chear, it is I,</hi> Mark 6. 50, 51, 52.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Is it ſo, that the ſalvations and deliverances that many of us have, are not until we be brought to extremities? then it is a word of Exhortation; Then look up to God in the moſt deſperate caſe, when you know not what to do in your Storms at Sea, in your Straits at Land. O then let your eyes be up unto the Lord; you ſee how many deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have come down in extremities, as anſwers to Prayer. O Pray hard; let go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Sea, being in Storms at Sea, being brought to Extremities at Sea, learn you to Pray.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:38362:87"/>
            <head>PRAYERS.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The Mariners Prayer.</head>
               <p>O GOD the great Creator of Heaven and Earth, thou doſt whatſoever thou pleaſeſt in the Sea, and in all deep places; I, the moſt unworthieſt of all thy Servants am at this time called upon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thy Wonders in the Deep, and to perform my Duty in great Waters. Guide me, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, in all times and in all places: Be thou our skilful Pilot to ſteer us, and protect us from all Dangers, and rebuke the Winds and the Seas when they moleſt us, preſerve our Veſſel from being rent by the loud cracks of Thunder, or from being burnt by Lightning or any other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident; keep us and ſave us from tempeſtuous Weather, from bitter Froſts, Hail, Ice, Snow, or Whirlwinds, and from Captivity and Slavery.</p>
               <p>TEACH me, O God, to remember thee my Creator in the days of my Youth, to continually think upon thee, and to praiſe thy Name for all thy Mercies: Bleſs all our Friends, I beſeech thee, that are on Land, and let their Prayers for us be acceptable in thy ſight, and grant that our next meeting together may be for the better, and not for the worſe, even to the praiſing and magnifying of thy Holy Name, and Salvation of our own Souls in the great day of the Lord Jeſus, to whom with thee, and thy bleſſed Spirit, be aſcribed all Honour, Power, and Glory, Adoration, and Subjection, now and for evermore.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer before a Voyage.</head>
               <p>O ETERNAL God, even the God of our Salvation, the hope of all the ends of the Earth, and of them that remain in the wide
<pb facs="tcp:38362:87"/>
Ocean, under the ſhadow of whoſe Wings we are always ſecure, and without whoſe protection we cannot expect ſafety; I have been, O Lord, preſerved by thee until this moment from many dangers, for which I have not expreſſed my thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in acknowledging thoſe dayly bleſſings I have received from thee; but, O Lord, forget and forgive thoſe mani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>old ſins which I have committed againſt thee, and blot them out of thy Book of remembrance.</p>
               <p>PURGE me, O Lord, I beſeech thee, from all vile affections; and grant I may bring forth the fruits of thy Spirit; go along with me with thy bleſſed Spirit in this my Voyage, preſerve me from Pirates, Robbers and Enemies, defend me from Rocks, Sands and Shelves, and keep me from Thunder and Lightning, Storms and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous Weather, or any other danger that may diſmay me. To thee, O Lord, I commend my Body and Spirit, to diſpoſe of me according to thy holy Will and Pleaſure; if thou art pleas'd to call for my life upon the ſurface of the Waters; I know thy Almighty Word can command the Sea to give up her Dead at the laſt and great audit.</p>
               <p>But if thou haſt determin'd to bring me ſafe to my deſired Haven, give me thy Grace which is ſufficient for me to walk according to thy holy Will in all things; make me to lay hold of Eternal Life, which as the Anchor of Hope, is both ſure and ſtedfaſt; keep me from all tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations ghoſtly and bodily, and from ſudden Death, and in thy good time bring me to the Land of the Living, there to reign with thee for evermore.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Thanksgiving after a Voyage.</head>
               <p>O IMMORTAL God, I have ſeen thy Works O Lord, and thy Wonders in the
<pb facs="tcp:38362:88"/>
deep; thou ſpakeſt the Word and the ſtorm Wind aroſe, which lifted up the Waves thereof but when we cried unto thee, thou madeſt the ſtorm to ceaſe, ſo that the Waves thereof were ſtill; then did we rejoyce becauſe we were a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and thou broughteſt us ſafe to that Haven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> where we would be: O that men would there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore praiſe thee, O Lord, for thy Goodneſs, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Wonders thou doſt continually for them.</p>
               <p>I BLESS thy Holy Name, for conducting me through thoſe many dangers which encompaſſed me, and praiſe thy Mercy that the Deep hath not ſwallowed me up, and that I am not gone down into the place of ſilence. I alſo praiſe thy holy Name, and admire thy loving Kindneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, that thou haſt not delivered up my Body and Goods as a prey into the hands of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Men, but haſt brought me to my deſired Haven, and at laſt returned me back in ſafety to my Habitation.</p>
               <p>O LET me never forget to pay thoſe Vows I made to thee, when I was in trouble; but give me an awful ſenſe and apprehenſion of thy great Power, and poſſeſs my Soul with a true Reverence of thy Divine Majeſty; that I may evermore ſerve thee in holineſs and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs all the days of my Life: Endue me with thy Holy Spirit; that I may become acceptable in thy ſight, and may be fitted at length for future Glories, this I beg for thy Son Jeſus Chriſts ſake, my only Saviour.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer in a Storm.</head>
               <p>O LORD our God, thou haſt commanded us in the day of Calamity to call upon thy Name, and thou haſt promiſed to hear us; Lord, I fly unto thee, who art a ſure refuge; thy Flood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates
<pb facs="tcp:38362:88"/>
are opened, and the Floods lift up their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ofty Waves. But thou, O Lord moſt high, art mightier than the noiſe of many Waters: yea, than the mighty Waves of the Sea: Thou canſt in a moment, if it ſtand with thy Divine will and pleaſure, rebuke the Winds and the Sea, and turn this Storm into a Calm.</p>
               <p>I KNOW I juſtly deſerve to be caſt away, and utterly to be rejected by thee; but Lord ſave us, or elſe we periſh; accept of my unfeigned ſorrow for all my ſins and tranſgreſſions, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due me with a ſtedfaſt reſolution to forſake them; be merciful unto us O God, be merciful unto us and ſave us from periſhing in theſe deep Waters; O refreſh us with thy Mercy, and that ſoon, leſt we go down into the place of ſilence, O comfort us in this great diſtreſs, that though the Sea rage and ſwell, our Hearts may be quiet and ſtill in this time of our diſconſolation.</p>
               <p>AND as I earneſtly deſire to be protected from this great peril and danger which now terrifies us, ſo I earneſtly beſeech thee, that thou wilt for ever fill my heart with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch an awful dread of thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, that I may fear thy Name, and praiſe thy power in the great Congregation; awake my dull and drowſie Soul, from the ſloth of Sin, and renew a right Spirit within me; fill me with the gifts and Graces of thy Holy Spirit, that I may live the life of the Righteous, and never forget thy loving-kindneſs; ſave us now from Death I beſeech thee, from the mercile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Waves who are now ready to ſwallow us up, and bring us home in ſafety for thy Son Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, our only Lord and Saviour.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:38362:89"/>
               <head>A Thanksgiving after a Storm.</head>
               <p>I PRAISE and glorifie thy holy Name, O Lord, for all thy mercies and bleſſings vouchſafed unto me, eſpecially for this thy laſt great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, wherein I was incompaſſed in that wide Ocean, whom thou haſt ſet bounds and limits to; if thou, O Lord, hadſt not been on my ſide, the Sea had ſwallowed me up quick, and I had gone down into the deep of ſilence; but thou haſt been my God and my Deliverer, and haſt put a new Song into my Mouth, even a Song of Praiſe and Thankſgiving unto my God.</p>
               <p>I ACKNOWLEDGE O Lord, that thou art the God of all the Earth, and of them that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the broad Sea: Bleſſed for ever, and magnified be thy Name, that thou haſt not caſt me out of thy ſight, nor turned thy Mercy from me; I have eſcaped thy raging Sea, and the noiſe of the proud Waves have done me no harm, if thy Almighty Providence had not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected me, the ſtreams had gone over my Soul: But the ſtormy Wind and Tempeſt I have nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly eſcaped, the ſtorm is ceaſed, and I am ſafely delivered.</p>
               <p>AND now what ſhall I render to thee O Lord, for this, and all other thy great benefits? I will offer up unto thee the Sacrifice of Thankſgiving, and will pay thoſe vows I ſo ſolemnly made unto thee when I was in trouble; I will evermore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that my help is in the Lord, who made Heaven and Earth, and that thou art that God that can and will deliver me; let this thy mercy and loving kindneſs never depart my memory, but let me praiſe thy goodneſs, and ſing of thy power, unto my lives end.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:38362:89"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
